<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The present state of the German and Turkish empires, and remarks thereupon as also some peculiar reflections on the interest of the Christian princes : together with memoirs of the siege of Vienna, by an eminent officer in that city ... / by D.A., M.D.</title>
            <author>Abercromby, David, d. 1701 or 2.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 198KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B16512</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12880208</idno>
  <idno type="VID">199106</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240854149</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12880208</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B16512)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199106)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The present state of the German and Turkish empires, and remarks thereupon as also some peculiar reflections on the interest of the Christian princes : together with memoirs of the siege of Vienna, by an eminent officer in that city ... / by D.A., M.D.</title>
                  <author>Abercromby, David, d. 1701 or 2.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>78, [2], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for D. Brown ... and T. Goodwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Austro-Turkish War, 1683-1699.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Turkey --  History --  1453-1683.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Vienna (Austria) --  History --  Siege, 1683.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Europe --  Politics and government --  1648-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199106:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199106:1"/>
            <p>THE PRESENT STATE OF THE GERMAN and TURKISH EMPIRES, AND REMARKS thereupon: AS ALSO Some peculiar REFLECTIONS on the INTEREST of the CHRISTIAN PRINCES, Together with MEMOIRS Of the SIEGE of VIENNA, BY AN Eminent Officer in that CITY.</p>
            <p>With Observations on all the Accounts and Journals relating thereunto: And a true Account of the further Progress and great success of the Christian Forces, in the taking of <hi>BARKAN, GRAN,</hi> &amp;c. With an Historical PREFACE of the Rise and Growth of the <hi>Turkish</hi> Empire.</p>
            <p>By <hi>D. A.</hi> M. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>D. Brown,</hi> at the <hi>Black-Swan</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Temple-Barr;</hi> and <hi>T. Goodwin,</hi> at the <hi>Maidenhead,</hi> against St. <hi>Dunstans-Church</hi> in <hi>Fleetstreet,</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:199106:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199106:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>CHARLES</hi> Earl of <hi>MIDDLETON,</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary of State for the Affairs of <hi>SCOTLAND;</hi> and one of His MAJESTIES Most Honourable PRIVY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COƲNCIL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>'TIS not upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of a common, and fashionable Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom, that makes De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory Epistles as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to Books, as Livery to Servants, that I have adventured to present to your <hi>Honour</hi> these ensuing Papers; neither was it my design in this enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, to publish to the World your extraordinary Merit, since 'tis already sufficiently known both at home and abroad, by the choice His <hi>Majesty</hi> made of your <hi>Lordship</hi> to manage his more important concerns in the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Seat of <hi>Germany,</hi> where your
<pb facs="tcp:199106:3"/> Memory is still fresh, and your Repute beyond the reach of envy: Nor did I design by this small Present to take occasion, as I might easily have done, to publish the Illustrious, both Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Sufferings of your great Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in performance of his Duty to his King and Country. My Chief inducement then to present this small Piece to your <hi>Honour,</hi> was your full knowledge of the matters it treats of: For I am fully perswaded there are but few in this Nation, if there be any, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inform'd of the present State of <hi>Europe,</hi> and especially of <hi>Germany,</hi> of its true concerns, and interests: Your abode at <hi>Vienna,</hi> and your honourable employ there, gave you a fit opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to dive into the depth of the most important affairs; and having added unto the Nobility of your Blood, that of the Mind, by an universal knowledge, and not ordinary Learning, I may say, <hi>My Lord,</hi> without flattery, which I hate, <hi>Cane petus et angue,</hi> above all things, that there is no Subject written of that you are wholly a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to. You shall meet then with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:199106:3"/> in these following Discourses you are not already acquainted with; for what I say of the <hi>Othoman</hi> Emperors, you have, (no doubt) Read elsewhere more than once; and as to my reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons relating to the affairs of <hi>Germany,</hi> and other Princedoms of <hi>Europe,</hi> they cannot be unknown to your <hi>Honour,</hi> since you could not but see what so visibly flows from the premises sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd in this Treatise; which as I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to your Noble Partronage and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, so I do freely submit to your impartial Verdict and Censure, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing to testify thereby to the World, with how much Esteem and Respect</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am your <hi>Honours</hi> most Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Obedient Servant. D. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:199106:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199106:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Turks</hi> aspiring am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition is ingeniously re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented to us by a <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent,</hi> or Half-moon in its growth, with this speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Motto, <hi>Donec totum Impleat Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem,</hi> till it fill round its Orb, as if they pretended to the conquest of the whole world. And certainly if we reflect but a moment on the continual success they have still had against all their Enemies, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Christians or Mahumetans, we shall have reason to say, their pretences are not intirely groundless.</p>
            <p>They owe their first rise and aspiring to greatness, to the famous <hi>Tangropilix,</hi> their first King, who after the death of <hi>Mahomet</hi> the <hi>Persian</hi> Sultan, in the Battel of <hi>Ispaham</hi> in <hi>Persia,</hi> was, by an unanimous consent of both Armies, chose Sultan of <hi>Persia,</hi> and the Dominions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to that large Kingdom. So soon as he was seated in the Throne, the passage
<pb facs="tcp:199106:5"/> over <hi>Araxes</hi> first cleared of the Garisons that kept it, he called in his Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men▪ the <hi>Turks</hi> that lived then on the other side. He overthrew, in his return from his Expedition against the <hi>Arabians, Stephen</hi> the <hi>Greek</hi> Emperors Lieutenant in <hi>Media;</hi> resisted the Emperor <hi>Diogines,</hi> and left his Kingdom to his Son <hi>Axan,</hi> the second <hi>Turkish</hi> King, or the Sultan of <hi>Persia.</hi> This Prince had good success a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Emperor <hi>Diogines,</hi> whom he took Prisoner in a pitch'd Battle. As he was ready to encounter with <hi>Cultumuses,</hi> near the City of <hi>Eres,</hi> the <hi>Caliph</hi> of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon,</hi> a Priest of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> conjured them not to weaken the Religion of their great Prophet, by shedding each others Blood; but rather to stand to his award, which was consented to by them both, to the great damage of the poor Christians, who were on all sides invaded by the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Sarrazins,</hi> their own Divisions then, as now rendering them easie to be subdued. The Sultan by their agreement was to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy whatever he possessed, and his Cousin to possess in himself and his posterity, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever should be thence-forward Conquered on the Christians: This Ʋnion between
<pb facs="tcp:199106:5"/> the Sultan and his Cousin, occasioned the division of the <hi>Turkish</hi> Monarchy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solyman,</hi> Son to <hi>Cultumuses,</hi> Nephew to <hi>Tangropilix,</hi> made Wars against the Christians with various success: He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended obstinately what he had won from the Christians; but all this was but a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble to the Grandour of the <hi>Turkish</hi> Empire, founded first by the renowned <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoman.</hi> This fortunate Prince, after a full Victory over his less considerable Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, gave a great overthrow to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Princes, who had gathered their Forces together, in aim to raise the Siege of <hi>Prussia▪</hi> The civil dissentions, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testine embroyls amongst the <hi>Greeks,</hi> gave <hi>Othoman</hi> the opportunity to found his Empire in <hi>Phrygia</hi> and <hi>Bythinia.</hi> He was in these parts successful in all his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, insomuch that he mightily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased his Dominions having by this time subdued Twenty Cities with all their Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, and amongst the rest▪ <hi>Prussia;</hi> where, in the midst of his Victories he died and was buried. Here to this day his Tomb is to be seen. The <hi>Turks</hi> under his second Son <hi>Urkan,</hi> for his eldest Son died during his Regency, made great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress
<pb facs="tcp:199106:6"/> against the Christians; they ruin'd the Emperor <hi>Andronicus</hi> his Army, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered from the Christians, by Stratagem, the City of <hi>Nice;</hi> they took in the Two famous Castles of <hi>Sestos</hi> and <hi>Abydos,</hi> standing in <hi>Europe▪</hi> on the other side of the <hi>Hellesponte;</hi> got footing for the first time in <hi>Europe,</hi> where every day they grew more powerful by the sloth and cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardice of the Christians. Their first Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was at the Castle of <hi>Zembenick,</hi> they forced <hi>Callipolis</hi> to a surrender, after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving overthrown the Governor in a Pitch'd Battel. They continued their Warlike ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits under <hi>Amurath</hi> the first of that Name, who was in the beginning put to some trouble by the <hi>Turkish</hi> Princes in the lesser <hi>Asia,</hi> who envyed his aspiring am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, as fearing in the currant of his Victories, he might as well overthrow them as the Christians. But having vanquished them, he turned his Arms against <hi>Europe:</hi> He seized upon the Castle of <hi>Bernutum,</hi> and overthrew the <hi>Greeks,</hi> daring to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose him. Ʋnder his Conduct, the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans being cut off in a dreadful Battel, <hi>Hadrianople,</hi> now called <hi>Adrianople,</hi> was taken. He dispersed the Christian
<pb facs="tcp:199106:6"/> Army in <hi>Servia</hi> and <hi>Bulgaria,</hi> consisting of Fifty thousand Horse and Foot.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bajazet</hi> the first of that name succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and fell heavily on <hi>Servia;</hi> took in by surrender <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> the only City the Christians had in <hi>Asia.</hi> Having sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued <hi>Servia,</hi> and the greatest part of <hi>Bos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>san▪</hi> he invaded <hi>Thessalia,</hi> wasting it as he passed, with Fire and Sword, even to <hi>Thessalonica.</hi> He possessed himself of <hi>Neoplis</hi> in <hi>Greece,</hi> and <hi>Jocannia</hi> in <hi>Itolia;</hi> routed the Christians Besieging <hi>Neocopolis.</hi> He was at length defeated, and taken Prisoner by <hi>Tamarlain,</hi> who opposed him with Five hundred thousand Men Horse and Foot.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mahomet</hi> succeeded <hi>Bajazet,</hi> according to the most credible opinion; He restored the <hi>Turkish</hi> Kingdom ruined by the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars;</hi> He recovered all the Dominions his Father held in the greater <hi>Asia;</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw <hi>Musa</hi> in a Pitch'd Battel, and Commanded him, being taken, to be strangled; of whose Kingdom he took pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amurath</hi> the second increased, in a no small measure, the <hi>Turkish</hi> Empire; sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued <hi>Mustapha</hi> and his rebellious Army:
<pb facs="tcp:199106:7"/> He fell upon <hi>Hungary</hi> with Fire and Sword; cut off the Christians in a famous Battel with <hi>Vladislavus</hi> King of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and took in, by a free surrender, the great City of <hi>Sfetigrade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To <hi>Amarath</hi> the second, succeeded <hi>Mahomet</hi> the second, the first Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> for his many Victories sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named the <hi>Great.</hi> He possessed himself of <hi>Constantinople</hi> after a years Siege, brought <hi>Peloponesus</hi> into subjection, sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed upon <hi>Servia</hi> after the death of <hi>George Itsdespot;</hi> he invaded with success the Islands of the <hi>Egean Sea;</hi> he Attacked, and took in <hi>Sinope</hi> belonging to <hi>Usunca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sanus</hi> King of <hi>Persia,</hi> as also <hi>Tripeland</hi> by surrender. He Invaded <hi>Valaetria,</hi> and ruined it all by Fire and Sword. He Invaded the Islands in the <hi>Egaeum,</hi> and Landing on the Island of <hi>Milyllene,</hi> took the strong City from whence the Island takes its name; subdued the Kingdom of <hi>Bassan,</hi> and the Island of <hi>Eubea,</hi> now called <hi>Nigroponty.</hi> He conquered <hi>Ipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> and <hi>Dalmatia</hi> after the death of the renowned <hi>Scanderbeg;</hi> he overthrew in a Pitch'd Battel <hi>Usuncassanus</hi> King of <hi>Persia;</hi> he Besieged and took the rich City
<pb facs="tcp:199106:7"/> of <hi>Capha,</hi> sciruate near the shore in <hi>Taurica Chersonesus,</hi> a fruitful Country belonging to the <hi>Genoeses.</hi> The <hi>Turks,</hi> under this Emperors Reign, took in by Famine rather than by Force, the famous City of <hi>Croia,</hi> and under the Leading of <hi>Achmetes,</hi> Bassa, the Islands of <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyncthus</hi> and <hi>Cephalenia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mahomet</hi> being dead, <hi>Bajazet</hi> the second succeeded him: He overthrew his Brother <hi>Zemes,</hi> who had raised a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Army to wrestle with him for the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. He Stormed <hi>Kelly</hi> or <hi>Achilleia</hi> in <hi>Moldavia;</hi> took, by surrender, <hi>Tarsus</hi> in <hi>Cilicia.</hi> The <hi>Turks</hi> about this time gave a great overthrow to <hi>Pyraner</hi> King of <hi>Caramania;</hi> and some years after inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Podolia</hi> and <hi>Russia,</hi> spoyling the Country, and Sacking several Walled Towns. <hi>Scanderbassa, Bajazet's</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant in <hi>Illyria,</hi> broke in upon the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Country of <hi>Friuli,</hi> belonging to the <hi>Venetians,</hi> on the Borders of <hi>Italy. Naw-Pactum,</hi> or <hi>Lepanto</hi> was surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to <hi>Bajazet</hi> by Treatise, all succour being dispaired. He took also by sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise the strong City of <hi>Mentom,</hi> now called <hi>Modon;</hi> upon which, several other
<pb facs="tcp:199106:8"/> Cities belonging to the <hi>Venetians</hi> yielded upon Composition. This mighty Emperor vanquished in Battel <hi>Selimus</hi> Governour of <hi>Trepisomd,</hi> who had conspired against him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Selimus,</hi> Successor to <hi>Bajazet,</hi> gave no small increase to the <hi>Turkish</hi> Empire; He took in, by a furious Storm, <hi>Callamas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum,</hi> a City of the <hi>Persians;</hi> he subdued the Kingdom of <hi>Alladeuctes,</hi> the City of <hi>Alleppo,</hi> the great <hi>Caire,</hi> and all other Cities in <hi>Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Soliman</hi> the Magnificent, the first of that Name, and the fourth <hi>Turkish</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, Governed the <hi>Turkish</hi> Empire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Selimus.</hi> He Besieged, and took in at length the City of <hi>Rhode,</hi> the City of <hi>Buda,</hi> and others in <hi>Hungaria:</hi> His Fleet under the Command of <hi>Barbarossa,</hi> burn'd <hi>Rhegium,</hi> carried away the Garison and Citizens. Himself in person made the Conquest of <hi>Strigonium,</hi> and <hi>Albariga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> after many terrible Assaults. And by the Conduct of his Lieutenant <hi>Achme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> he possessed himself of the Cities of <hi>Temesvar,</hi> and <hi>Polnuck</hi> in <hi>Hungaria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Soliman</hi> being dead, upon the return of the Army from <hi>Hungaria</hi> towards
<pb facs="tcp:199106:8"/>
               <hi>Constantinople, Selimus</hi> the second of that Name, was declared Emperour. <hi>He</hi> conquered <hi>Nicosia,</hi> a City standing in a Plain and Champaign Ground, together with the whole Island of <hi>Cyprus, Tama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gausta,</hi> and other places. The <hi>Turks,</hi> under this Prince, overran all <hi>Moldavia</hi> and <hi>Valachia,</hi> took in the strong Castle of <hi>Goul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letta,</hi> and the new Castle built at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of <hi>Don John,</hi> in his Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion against the <hi>Moorish</hi> Rebels; as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise the City and Kingdom of <hi>Tunis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After <hi>Selimus's</hi> Death, <hi>Amurath</hi> the Third of that Name, and Sixth Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the <hi>Turks,</hi> took possession of the Empire. He entred into <hi>Russia,</hi> where he burn'd and destroyed two Hundred Castles, besides a great number of Towns and Villages: he made a considerable progress against the <hi>Persians,</hi> and gave them several overthrows in divers pitch'd Battles. His Forces took in <hi>Veylits</hi> the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of <hi>Croatia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amurath</hi> dead, <hi>Mahomet</hi> the third of that Name, and seventh Emperour of the <hi>Turks,</hi> took upon him to Govern the <hi>Turkish</hi> Empire, he Besieged, and took in, by Surrender, <hi>Agria,</hi> routed the
<pb facs="tcp:199106:9"/> Christian Army, defended <hi>Buda</hi> against the Christians, defeated them coming to relieve <hi>Canifiae,</hi> which was surrendered to the <hi>Turks,</hi> who immediately forrag'd the Country of <hi>Stiria.</hi> They possessed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves likewise of <hi>Albaregalis;</hi> they spoil'd and plunder'd it, and put to the Sword all the Soldiers and Citizens.</p>
            <p>Ʋpon the death of <hi>Mahomet</hi> the third, his Son <hi>Achmat,</hi> then but Fifteen years of Age, was by the great Bassas, and high Officers, saluted Emperour. His Forces broke violently into <hi>Valuhia</hi> a <hi>Vicegrade,</hi> in the juncture of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine troubles. <hi>Achmat</hi> ravaged <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>silvania</hi> with a powerful Army, of which <hi>Bethelem Gabor</hi> was acknowledged Prince under his protection; and so it was rent from the <hi>German</hi> Empire.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turkish</hi> Empire was no less, but rather more illustrious under <hi>Osman</hi> the first of that Name, and the Tenth Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the <hi>Turks:</hi> Ʋnder this Prince they put the <hi>Persians</hi> to flight in a great Battel, and entered into the Heart of <hi>Persia,</hi> wasting with Fire and Sword all that stood in their way. This Emperour caused a great Fleet of Galleys to put
<pb facs="tcp:199106:9"/> to Sea, which spoiled the Coast of <hi>Sicilia,</hi> and Landing Five Thousand <hi>Turks</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> surprised the strong Town of <hi>Manfredonia,</hi> and then joyning with the Pyrats of <hi>Argiers,</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> made a descent in the Island of <hi>Janisa</hi> near <hi>Majorca,</hi> possessed by the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> in which Island they got great booty. <hi>Osman</hi> in person reduced <hi>Moldavia</hi> to the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the new <hi>Waywod.</hi> He entred <hi>Podolia 1621.</hi> Sack'd and Burn'd what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he met with in his way; and made an Infinite Number of Slaves.</p>
            <p>In the Reign of <hi>Amurath</hi> the fourth, <hi>Babylon,</hi> after a long Siege, was recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of the hands of the <hi>Persians,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which the Grand Signiour put a Garison of Thirty thousand Men Horse and Foot. So the <hi>Turks</hi> cleared of all their Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stik broyls, became more terrible than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to all their Enemies, and are now the powerfullest Nation in <hi>Europe,</hi> under the command of <hi>Memet,</hi> or <hi>Mehomet</hi> the fourth of that Name, and the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Emperour of the <hi>Turks.</hi> They have under him conquered the strong City of <hi>Varadine, New-Hausel, Clovino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palis,</hi> the famous City of <hi>Candia,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:199106:10"/> the impregnable fortress of <hi>Kaminiech,</hi> which opened to 'em a passage throw all <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolia</hi> and <hi>Volhinia</hi> to the Walls of <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis.</hi> Out of all this, we see clearly, that the <hi>Turkish</hi> Empire is founded on the overthrow of the four great Monarchies, viz. The <hi>Assyrian, Grecian, Persian,</hi> and the <hi>Roman;</hi> The <hi>Turks</hi> being now in Possession of <hi>Babylon, Chaldea, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea,</hi> a great part of <hi>Persia,</hi> all <hi>Greece,</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> with the greatest part of <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia,</hi> the Islands of <hi>Cyprus, Rhodes, Mityllene, Nigroponto, Kio, Candia, &amp;c.</hi> The Empire of <hi>Trepesand, Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grellia, Tunis, Argiers, Dalmatia; Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyria, Tribullenia,</hi> the Countrys of <hi>Transilvania, Valachia, Moldavia,</hi> and <hi>Bulgaria,</hi> the greatest part of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia,</hi> and all the Sea-Coast from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of <hi>Epidaurus</hi> to the utmost limits of their Empire in <hi>Europe</hi> Westward, into the mouth of the Riveo <hi>Tanxais,</hi> withal that lyeth between <hi>Buda</hi> and <hi>Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:199106:10"/>
            <head>The State of the GERMAN AND Turkish Empire, AND THE <hi>Siege of Vienna, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE design of this Treatise, being only intended to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise the State of Affairs, as they now are: What we have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iled in the Preface serves only as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ort Narrative of the Advance of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Monarchy; wherein as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is so well known to most people,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:199106:11"/> the method may seem more short, then otherwise requisite, though e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough perhaps for those that have not the convenience, or leisure of peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing a larger Volume. Now since brevity is proposed, I come immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to the matter, and say that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this Empire of the <hi>Turks</hi> be arrived to such a Bulk, and prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous extent; I cannot think it so ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible to the World, as to discourage the uniting of the Christian Princes in the attempt of its overthrow: Nay I am so far from thinking them not enough, that provided <hi>Germany</hi> alone were not divided into so many petty Principalities, it would prove more then an equal match for the <hi>Turks.</hi> But supposing things as they are, and that the Empire of <hi>Germany</hi> is suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently stored with an infinite number of Warlike Men, and no want of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced Officers; what need we have recourse to this almost impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble endeavour of ever reducing of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> under the absolute Command of one Monarch, since it may as it now stands, be too considerable an
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:199106:11"/> Adventure for the whole <hi>Ottoman</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The <hi>Turks</hi> though very consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, and exceeding in number, have their chiefest strength consisting in the body of their <hi>Janizaries,</hi> which do not amount to more then Forty Thousand Men. Their <hi>Spahy's</hi> or <hi>Turkish</hi> Horse, except some choice Troops are very insignificant, and much inferior to the <hi>German Cavalry</hi> in Valour and Discipline. The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> likewise, who commonly make a Great Figure, by their vast number in the grand Signiors Armies, are but mean Souldiers, and more terrible to the Peasants, then to regular Forces. A handful of Christians have often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times defeated without any considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel loss, many Thousands of them The <hi>Germans</hi> have another consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able advantage, if they would join unanimously against the <hi>Turks,</hi> which is this. The River <hi>Danube</hi> runs East<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward into the Black Sea, not very far from <hi>Constantinople,</hi> through the grand Signiors best Territories, washing the Walls of his best Cities. This fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisheth the <hi>Germans</hi> with a great op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:199106:12"/> of sending easily, and with small expences and less time, all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessaries requisite for the equipping and providing for their Armies; In so much as if they undertook the Siege of <hi>Buda,</hi> or any other <hi>Ottoman</hi> Garrison situated on, or near the River; they could easily from all parts of <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> convey to their Forces, Guns, Powder, Shot, Hay, Oats, and whatsoever else it stood in need of; in case the Adjacent Country were ruin'd, and could af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford them nothing. All this might be done without fear of any consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able dammage or danger from the Enemies, either by building Forts here and there for the security of the passage, or by furnishing the Boats with such a number of Men, as would be judged necessary for their defence: Or which would still be a surer work by attacking first the nearest Towns, standing on the River, and then go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing along with the Current. If the <hi>Turks</hi> had had the same advantage for the Conquest of <hi>Germany,</hi> I fear it had been long ago a Province of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:199106:12"/>
               <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire: Whereas now their provisions of the <hi>Turks,</hi> must of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity come to their Armies by Land, with great trouble, evident danger, and at vast expence. In the late Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> they had need of no less then all <hi>Tekely's</hi> Forces, with an Army of <hi>Tartars</hi> to secure their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voys, which notwithstanding their best measures, were oftentimes sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised by the Christians: So that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can encourage the <hi>Ottomans</hi> to attack <hi>Germany,</hi> but the continual broyls and divisions, more frequent in this Age we live in, amongst Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, then amongst the <hi>Turks,</hi> or any other <hi>Infidels.</hi> And I am fully perswaded the Grand Visier had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver adventured to be siege <hi>Vienna,</hi> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving after him, <hi>Gomorrha, Raab, Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buy,</hi> and the Island of <hi>Schutgz;</hi> if he had not hoped, and perhaps also been well informed before hand, that the <hi>German</hi> Princes, at least the most considerable, either could not, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of some troublesome Neighbours, or would not send their Forces to its relief.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:199106:13"/>
            <p>Upon another account too the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> cannot but be terrible to the <hi>Turks,</hi> and fit to do great things: For they have for several years of late been in Wars with the <hi>French</hi> and with such success, that they gave them an entire overthrow at <hi>Treve,</hi> in the plain between the <hi>Sar</hi> and <hi>Mosel,</hi> and took by siege <hi>Philipsburg,</hi> the strongest hold the <hi>French</hi> had in <hi>Germany.</hi> So we may look upon them now, as Souldiers trained up and capable of great enterprises. The Duke of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain</hi> their General, and the rest of their Chief Officers, being all Men of great courage and conduct; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the <hi>Turks,</hi> since the siege of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> have made no considerable Wars, except for a short while against the <hi>Poles,</hi> by whom they were worsted: So it is more then probable they may be undone by the Christians, before time, and opportunity furnish them with good and experienced Officers; the most part of their prime Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders at <hi>Candy,</hi> being either dead, or unfit for service.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:199106:13"/>
            <p>But now if we reflect but a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, how terrible the King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> is of late become to the <hi>Turks,</hi> we shall easily be convinced of the Truth of what I have said. For pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided he, and the Emperour, stand close to their offensive, and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive league, what may the Christians fear, or rather what success may they not pretend to, if they resolve upon a War against the <hi>Turks?</hi> I doubt not but these two Princes, with their sole Forces, if not hindred by intestine broils, by Foreign Enemies, or by the jealousy of some <hi>Turkishly</hi> affected Christians, would in a very short time reduce all <hi>Hungary</hi> to the <hi>German</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, which must be the first step to the Weakning of the Grand Signiors power in <hi>Europe.</hi> And as for the method of undertaking, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a constant War against the <hi>Turks;</hi> this methinks, would prove absolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the best. The Emperour, and the King of <hi>Polands</hi> being as they are now United together, must be supplied by the Christian Princes with Mony, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then with Men, because <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:199106:14"/> and <hi>Poland,</hi> may furnish a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Men sufficient, for the conquest of the whole <hi>Turkish</hi> Empire, or at least capable to hinder their further progress into Christendom. But, if any Christian Prince would send Men only and not Mony, their number must be such, as shall be judged con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient by the Emperour, lest seeing themselves too strong, they became on a suddain, Enemies.</p>
            <p>For this reason therefore, though the <hi>French</hi> King, has ever been will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to send into <hi>Germany</hi> twenty, or thirty thousand Men against the <hi>Turks,</hi> they were never accepted of, because of the dangerous consequences of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting into the bowels of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, such a powerful Army; which might prove more fatal to it, then the Enemy it self.</p>
            <p>Some few thousands of the <hi>French,</hi> would do better service in this case, then a whole Army, which besides the jealousy might be occasioned, would perhaps expect too much, and not easily obey the General of the Empire. The measures the <hi>German</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:199106:14"/> Princes are to take must be not only to furnish their Quota (or part) in Mony, but also in Men, though not to exceed so in number, as to give cause of jealousy to the Emperour or other <hi>German</hi> Princes; and for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies sake and other good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, are to be raised in <hi>Germany.</hi> But as for the <hi>French,</hi> if they be not for their own ends, as they are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally asserted to be, and on that account well-wishers to the <hi>Turbant,</hi> the best service they can do the Empire, is not to trouble it, or hinder the <hi>German</hi> Princes from sending the proportion of their Forces against the <hi>Turks,</hi> as may be done by keeping on their fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers a formidable Army, which is a no less efficacious way of making War in concurrence to the <hi>Turks</hi> interest, then by an open irruption into the midst of <hi>Germany,</hi> whilst it is attack't by that powerful, and irreconcilable Enemy.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Italian</hi> Princes, may supply the Emperour, both with Men, and Mony; incouraged by the good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:199106:15"/> is highly to be commended in regard of his Zeal towards the promoting of the Christian Interest; and the great sums of Mony he has furnisht the Emperour with in this Important con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Venetians</hi> are not alittle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the conservation of the Empire, and may easily supply the Emperours wants with Mony, and Men likewise, if it were not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps judged more expedient, they should make a <hi>puissant</hi> diversion, as they may easily do both by Sea and by Land; they alone having often for several years resisted that formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>puissance,</hi> not without considerable loss. And I am of opinion they had never a better opportunity, then in this present conjuncture. For it's cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, the <hi>Turks</hi> are exceedingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by reason of their bad success at <hi>Vienna;</hi> the best of their Troops being defeated, and consequently the strength of their Expire extreamly Weakned. So that should the <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> make use of the occasion and Invade them by Sea, and by Land in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:199106:15"/> a mutual Confederacy with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of <hi>Germany,</hi> it is not to be doubted but that they would either force the <hi>Turks</hi> to a shameful, and disadvantageous Peace, or to War, which could not at length, but prove fatal to their Empire.</p>
            <p>Now the Persian, who▪ has no greater Enemy then the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Emperour, would undoubtedly lay hold on this occasion, for the retak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and other his Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories possessed by the <hi>Turks.</hi> This Prince gave great marks of his Joy, when he heard of the total over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the <hi>Turks</hi> at <hi>Lepanto,</hi> and resolved to invade them soon after with 200000 Men, if the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans had not by their too ordinary di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visions rendered ineffectual that great Victory. And it's not to be doubted but that so soon as the now <hi>Persian</hi> King, shall be informed of the great overthrow the <hi>Turks</hi> have received before <hi>Vienna,</hi> he will be in the same readiness, provided the Christian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces can but agree to lend a helping hand, and being at present in peace
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:199106:16"/> with all his Neighbours, especially with the great <hi>Mogul,</hi> he may make a puissant Diversion. Besides it may be hoped, that the malecontents of the <hi>Turkish</hi> Empire, who are in great number, may make use of this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion for their own safety, and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, few being under their Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances, for as ti's well known there is no such absolute Monarch in the World, as the Grand Signior; all his Subjects being but meer Slaves their Lives and Fortunes and all they have depending on his arbitrary dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Let us then look back upon the <hi>Turkish</hi> Subjects, as groaning under an unsupportable yoak, which they are ready to shake off, at the first occasion offered, which now seems to be by the unexpected Union of the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> and the happy conjuncture of a league, concluded between the Emperour and the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and if more is required by the overthrow of the flower of the <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kish</hi> Forces at <hi>Vienna.</hi> Besides, why may it not be believed that it's time
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:199106:16"/> for the <hi>Greeks</hi> to rouse up their drowsy Spirits, and conceive some hopes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain of their ancient liberty. They want not in the midst of their suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and slavery undaunted Men, that wait upon all occasions to draw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, with their Country, out of that unspeakable misery they now under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go. And since it's the cause of Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity why should we doubt of the assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of the <hi>Zaporazian Cossaks,</hi> always envious of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Prosperity, or despond of Providence perhaps never offering a fairer opportunity to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians of doing themselves and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try right by a timely piece of service? And if the <hi>Czars</hi> of <hi>Russia</hi> conceive any hopes of a revolution in the <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman</hi> Empire, we are not to think they will be idle, whilst the rest of the World is busy against the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemy; The <hi>Moscovites</hi> alone, are not an unequal match for the <hi>Turks,</hi> what then may they not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to, if they fall upon them in conjuction with the rest of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Forces, or whilst the <hi>Turks</hi> are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided at home by intestine Broyls, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:199106:17"/> Tumults, as undoubtedly it will hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in this conjuncture; and tis already credibly reported, that there are some commotions at <hi>Constantinople,</hi> occasion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the misfortune, and bad success of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army in <hi>Germany.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides it's observable the <hi>Moscovites</hi> can raise as powerful Armies, as the <hi>Turk</hi> himself, and Men more inured to fatigue and hardship. And because of several affronts they formerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the arrogance, and aspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ambition of the <hi>Turks,</hi> they are still (though at present in Peace) extreamly incensed against them, and infinitely desirous of some change of affairs in the <hi>Turkish</hi> Empire: That so they may with the greater security invade this potent Enemy.</p>
            <p>I confess the conjunction of two <hi>Czars</hi> to make one Soveraign, seems to divide that Empire and consequently Weaken it extremely; yet if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon their method of governing we need sear no ill consequence of of such a being of two heads in one body. For that they are fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded, their preservation, and sole
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:199106:17"/> happiness consists in their mutual a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, and constant corresponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which makes them go on unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mously, in all affairs of the publick concern, and suffer none in their Courts, that upon the account of their own Interest, would either sow, or spread the seed of division. It's to be supposed then, they understand so well their own concerns, as not to let pass this important occasion, to free themselves, and deliver the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians from the Barbarous attempts of the <hi>Turks;</hi> whose overthrow may be easier then we are as yet aware of; the most part of their Inland Cities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without any considerable Fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and those that are Frontiers, as New <hi>Hauset, Gran, Canise,</hi> being of no extraordinary force and their Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risons extreamly affrighted by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking <hi>Genius</hi> of the King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> whose heavy hand they have felt, more then once, and are like to feel as yet more hereafter: However this Prince has now an occasion, (which is thought he will not neglect,) to recover <hi>Kaminek</hi> and so free <hi>Poland</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:199106:18"/> from any further fear of the <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now his Troops being encouraged by the great success they have had in all their attempts against these In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, are the better disposed to the undertaking of greater things.</p>
            <p>So if this War continue, as we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive no great reason why it should not, we may live to see the <hi>Turks</hi> confined to the utmost parts of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> on theirside, and so their Moon from being a <hi>Crescent</hi> become a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crescent,</hi> yea and at length to dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish. <hi>Donec totum depleat Orbem,</hi> till it quited disappear: Which in all like li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood will happen, if the Chrislian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces will either agree to further this War, or at least give no disturbance to the Emperour, and the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> who are now the chief promoters thereof: How far it is their interest we shall easily understand by a short survey of the present State of <hi>Europe,</hi> in relation to the <hi>German</hi> affairs.</p>
            <p>And First, As to the <hi>Germans</hi> and <hi>Poles,</hi> no Man can doubt but that their greatest concern is the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the <hi>Turkish</hi> Monarchy,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:199106:18"/> which has so often threatned them with a total destruction. Neither can the State of <hi>Venice</hi> subsist long if the <hi>Turks</hi> make any considerable progress in <hi>Germany</hi> And we may look upon this Commonwealth as the only Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark of <hi>Italy.</hi> So that if it were once subdued, the rest of <hi>Italy, Genoa,</hi> perhaps, <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicilia</hi> excepted, would easily submit to the Enemy. A less potent Prince than the Grand Signior, which was, if I be not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staken, <hi>Charles</hi> the Eighth King of <hi>France,</hi> conquered all <hi>Italy</hi> in less than Nine months, though he quitted all again ere the year was expired. Neither are the Cities of <hi>Italy</hi> much better fortified now then they were then, and the <hi>Italians</hi> by sitting quiet at home have nothing of that Ancient Valour they were of old so renown'd for. So in all likelihood, if the <hi>Turks</hi> had taken <hi>Vienna? Italy</hi> had been but an easy conquest to them, and had not cost them much Blood. The Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> I confess, joyning all their Forces together, can make up a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable Army, but this Nation ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:199106:19"/> not been used in these latter times to Warlike expeditions, would in all likelihood be overpowered by the <hi>Turks.</hi> Now if <hi>Italy</hi> fell into the hands of these Infidels, <hi>Spain</hi> can never be able to resist such a potent Enemy. For this Kingdom is of late become so low, that it scarce retains any marks of its antient grandeur. The <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> seem now both to want Men, and Mony, yea and good Counsel too: So that by the little they could former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do against the <hi>Portuguise,</hi> and of late against the <hi>French,</hi> we may easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guess what is to be expected from them, if the <hi>Turks</hi> should happen to be their Neighbours? Though perhaps in such a conjuncture, their Liberties and Religion being at the Stake, they might do things beyond expectation</p>
            <p>But it's more probable then the contrary, that if the Grand Visie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had taken in <hi>Vienna</hi> by storm, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by surrender, he had first subdued and that without any opposition <hi>Styr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Carinthia</hi> and <hi>Austria; Gomorrha, Raab Presburg,</hi> the Island of <hi>Schutz</hi> coul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not hold out after the taking of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:199106:19"/> as having no further Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication with <hi>Germany.</hi> The Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood of the <hi>Turks,</hi> had instantly the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> upon a seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deliberation, what measures they were to take in such a conjuncture The Grand Signior had hindred them easily from uniting together their Forces, partly by fear, partly by fair promiles of Friendship and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection to all such as either would joyn with him, or be but lookers on. And in this case, some both <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists</hi> and Protestants would have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with the Infidels, because of the present danger: And who knows how by force some unthinking Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants might be prevailed with, or allured by a specious pretence (of which sort I hope there is none how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever) to hope for greater freedom of Conscience under the <hi>Turks,</hi> then under the Emperor, and by that means through an inconsiderate Zeal, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their Vassals, in opposition only to Popery, against the professors whereof, perhaps they have some reason to be averse; yet should the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:199106:20"/>
               <hi>Turk</hi> prevail, what would be the end, but in time an Establishment of Mahometanism instead of Christiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which is the consequence where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the <hi>Turks</hi> become absolute Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters; neither can the Papists pretend to a more infallible resolution to the contrary, then the Protestants. But why do I dwell so long upon this sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, for no Man that knows the difference will elect the former (<hi>viz.</hi> Mahometanism) and nothing but a locall necessity can force the latter (meaning <hi>Romanism.</hi>) But to return to what hath been said, to wit, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the <hi>Turks</hi> are absolute Masters Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometanism will take footing, which we see has hapned in all the <hi>Eastern</hi> Countries, for though there be as yet a handful of Christians in <hi>Asia, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolia, Grecia, Romania,</hi> &amp;c. it's a thing worth observation, that in less then 200 years the Christian Religion has almost ceased in all the <hi>Eastern</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, notwithstanding it had for more then a thousand years before been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest in these parts.</p>
            <p>The same would be the fate of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:199106:20"/>
               <hi>Germany,</hi> if the <hi>Turks</hi> overcame them, the third or at the utmost the fourth generation would begin to Sing the Praises of <hi>Mahomet?</hi> And look upon Christs Divinity as a Dream. Now after what hath been said, 'tis pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed none will be fond of a change, nor from their Hearts, desire the <hi>Turks</hi> Prosperity: If there be any such, let them own what name, or Religion they please but that of a Christian, which it's to be feared they cannot be; and then I have no more to say to them in that particular. But touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Topick of Interest; I would fain know what their opinion is about the <hi>Turkish</hi> yoak, and that of their own Prince, as to its easiness and lightness; wherein if they do not as in Religion run from one error in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another, they cannot but see the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, and find how miserably, and in what distress the <hi>Turkish</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects live in. Where they have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a property in life, nor substance. Where the Arbitrary will of the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan and his subordinates is the only Law current. Where they are Bond-Slaves,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:199106:21"/> not free born Subjects. Where that which is accounted an honour among Christians is a shame, in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their Daughters made Whores to the <hi>Seraglio;</hi> and their Sons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides being brought up in another Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, taught to cut their own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and Kindreds Throats. And since this, and a great deal more, that might be said, must be patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly suffered, I cannot think any one will be so obstinately perverse, as to think of exchanging his obedience to a Christian Prince and Religion, for that of a Pagan and Tyrant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some perhaps will think I have run on too far in this unnecessary Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox, and be apt to retort that though <hi>Vienna</hi> had been taken by the <hi>Turks,</hi> there was no great fear of his further progress into <hi>Germany:</hi> Because <hi>Lewis</hi> the King of <hi>France</hi> (surnarned the great) for the great things he has done already, would oppose him in such a case with a <hi>puissant</hi> Army, and force him back again to the great loss of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and his own immortal Glory.</p>
            <p>This indeed would be great in <hi>Lewis</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:199106:21"/> the Great; and in Truth in such a conjuncture of affairs he would be the only Prince of <hi>Europe</hi> in a capacity to stop the progress of such a potent Enemy. But First, we may justly question whether he would in such a case be willing, or not, till such time as he were forced to it, for his own defence. For every one knows that knows any thing, that clipping the wings of the <hi>Austrian</hi> Eagle (or House of <hi>Austria</hi>) will extremely add to the splendour of the <hi>French</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy. Whilst then the <hi>Turks</hi> were invading <hi>Germany</hi> on the one side, would not both Self-preservation Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Interest invite the <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ench</hi> King to be busy on the other? A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d divide perhaps <hi>Germany</hi> with the <hi>Tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ks,</hi> since in all likelihood he could do no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Yea this it seems, might prove his only expedient to put himself in a condition to oppose afterwards the <hi>Turkish</hi> fury by seizing first upon the Neighbouring holds, and Cities of <hi>Germany,</hi> as not being able to defend themselves. Would not he be then strangely tempted to attack <hi>Philips<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:199106:22"/> Mayence, Spire, Manem, Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minstean,</hi> &amp;c. rather then suffer such places, to fall into the hands of the <hi>Turks;</hi> or defend'em for the <hi>Germans,</hi> from whom perhaps he would scarce get thanks, and who might prove af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward his mortal Enemies. He has been hovering these many years over <hi>Millan, Genoa, Flanders, Holland,</hi> and threatning <hi>England</hi> too afar off. The good success of the <hi>Turks</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> would present him with the fittest oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion can be imagined, for such in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprises. And if it may be feared, as things now stand, that <hi>Flanders</hi> will have much ado to escape him; in such a conjuncture, there had been no hopes of saving it from the <hi>French</hi> yoak. <hi>Flanders</hi> oweth the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning part of its Liberties to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Germany,</hi> who obliged the <hi>French,</hi> to withdraw the best part of their Troops from <hi>Flanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All <hi>Europe</hi> knows into what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream distress the States of <hi>Holland</hi> were brought by the <hi>French</hi> Kings first and second Campagne against the <hi>Hollanders:</hi> And had <hi>Germany</hi> been
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:199106:22"/> invaded by the <hi>Turks,</hi> the <hi>Lillies</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps had ere now taken such deep roots in <hi>Holland,</hi> that it had not been easy (to say no more) to pull them out again. But as <hi>Germany</hi> was then in Peace with the <hi>Turks,</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour united all the <hi>German</hi> Princes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, for their common interest, and set on foot in the beginning of Winter, an Army of near 40000 Horse and Foot, under the Command of <hi>Muntecuculy,</hi> who at his first arrival besieged and took in by surrender the City of <hi>Bonn,</hi> belonging to the Bishop of <hi>Cullen.</hi> The good success whereof oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casioned a great change in the affairs of <hi>Holland.</hi> For then the <hi>French</hi> thought it no longer secure for them to remain there, and deserted on a sudden the Cities they had taken in it partly by force; partly by a free surrender, so that after having caused the Citizens to redeem their Liberties with great sums of Mony the <hi>French</hi> retreated from their new conquests, which they had never done, if the forces of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> had been diverted by a <hi>Turkish</hi> invasion.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:199106:23"/>
            <p>Great <hi>Britain</hi> I grant if in Peace at home may prove alway a suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient protection for <hi>Holland,</hi> and the Low Countries. Yet in case there had been no hopes of help, or diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion from <hi>Germany,</hi> by reason of the <hi>Turks,</hi> invading it, <hi>France</hi> by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the Neighbourhood, and so many strong Cities it possesseth, in in the Low Countries, had in all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance swallowed up, that small re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> before <hi>England</hi> could be in a readiness to relieve them. Now the <hi>Spanish</hi> Towns being once conquered, by the <hi>French, Holland</hi> would either submit to the yoak up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on fair conditions, or could but make a very feeble resistance. So that their only safety in such a desperate case would be an intire submission to the King of <hi>England,</hi> and so acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him as their Prince and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign. Which would engage him to defend 'em with the same Zeal he would defend <hi>England</hi> it self.</p>
            <p>Out of all this Discourse, we may gather, that although the <hi>French</hi> King
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:199106:23"/> were able alone to beat the <hi>Turks</hi> out of <hi>Germany,</hi> in case they had succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their designs; it's not certain whether he would have been willing to do it, at least till he had been him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self possest of the best part of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> of <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> likewise. Which some of these People would perhaps have no less willingly bore, then the Slaveries under the <hi>Turkish</hi> yoak: So great is their Aversion to the <hi>French</hi> Subjection. But let us invert the Medal, and take another view of <hi>Germany.</hi> I assert that if <hi>Vienna</hi> had been taken, it had not been easy for the <hi>French,</hi> to hinder the <hi>Turks,</hi> from overpowering <hi>Germany,</hi> yea and <hi>France</hi> too, within a shorter time then we do perhaps imagine. How unhappy then would this dissatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Christian Princes have proved to all the Christian World, and whitherto would they have ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? If we may guess, or following the opinion of many People it's more then probable that a Peace or a Truce had immediately ensued. Which the <hi>Turks</hi> would no doubt have willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly consented to, in order to the setling
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:199106:24"/> their affairs in this Imperial City, and the adjacent Countries. But how fatal this Peace had proved to all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> we may easily guess, if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect but a moment on the <hi>Turks</hi> true interest, in such a conjuncture. For then all the Ambitious and Malecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented Persons of <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> had flocked to him for support and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief which he would undoubtedly have promised, and in some measure per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, being so necessary in this affair in order to his further progress. Nay rather then fail made his Application to the Protestant Princes in <hi>Germany,</hi> as being well perswaded of their aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion against Popery, with hopes to draw them to his side by promises of great advantages and a full liberty to serve God after their own manner.</p>
            <p>But after making all the interest he could on this side, he would not forget to fortify himself on the other, by setling in <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> the whole strength of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire. He would have easily lodged in <hi>Hungary,</hi> and the Hereditary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces 150000 fighting Men, who all this Winter long had not been idle,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:199106:24"/> but either exacting contributions, or seizing upon paslages, fit for their designs, or building Forts, or Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the Frontier Towns. And the longer this Peace had lasted, the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler afterwards they had been either to defend themselves or attack others. But I hear some answering the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians Princes in this conjuncture would be no less busy, then the <hi>Turks,</hi> for their own preservation, and would joyn alltogather as one Man against this common Enemy.</p>
            <p>If we may judge of things to come, by what is past, we have no reason to think they would, though reason enough to think they should. For as the jealousy of the <hi>French</hi> King's growing Power, hinders the Union of <hi>Germany;</hi> the Neighbouring Princes, as the <hi>Palatine</hi> the Arch-bishop of <hi>Treve,</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Spicee, Mayen,</hi> &amp;c. dare not withdraw from his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, lest, what would undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happen, they were eaten up, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Empire could be in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to help them: Even so it would happen in the other case the <hi>German</hi> Princes Neighbours to the <hi>Turks</hi> being
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:199106:25"/> forced in such a situation of affairs, to comply with the Grand Signiors inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, which then would prove in some measure theirs. As for <hi>England,</hi> mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a little World by it self, and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing but it self, it would not be much concerned, with what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress the <hi>Turks</hi> could make in <hi>Germany,</hi> since thereby its great trading by Sea, could suffer no diminution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France,</hi> as I said before, would look to its own interest, and perhaps share with the <hi>Turks,</hi> by taking from the <hi>Germans,</hi> what they could not keep for themselves. And the <hi>Spaniards</hi> not being able to send an Army into the Low Countries, sufficient to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend'em from the <hi>French,</hi> perhaps more for want of Mony then Men, the <hi>Turk</hi> would have little reason to fear them, and less as yet the <hi>Italian</hi> Princes, as being neither so potent, nor so warlike, nor very well fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished with Monies to raise considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Forces, nor very willing if they could, many of them being very indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, whether the Cross, or the <hi>Turbant</hi> be most prevalent provided they enjoy their petty Estates in peace and ease:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:199106:25"/> Which the Grand Signior under the terms of the ordinary tribute, would easily grant'em. And foreseeing this would be the worst of it, they would not prove very jealous of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Grandeur, but would perhaps in time make up their Peace with the Enemies to their best advantage. Let us now return to <hi>France</hi> again which gave oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to this discourse, and examin impartially, if it be in a posture to beat the <hi>Turks</hi> (supposed already Masters of <hi>Vienna</hi>) out of <hi>Germany,</hi> in case the <hi>French</hi> thorow a disinteressed Zeal, for the good of Christendom, would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake such an Important War.</p>
            <p>I confess the <hi>French</hi> Empire, is grown to such a pitch that it is become terrible▪ not only to the Neighbouring Nations, but also to the <hi>Turks</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, whom they defeated in the Battle of <hi>Raah,</hi> under the Command of the <hi>German</hi> General <hi>Montecuculy; Colligny</hi> and <hi>De la Feullad,</hi> were their immediate Leaders. Being but 4 or 5 Thousand they worsted the <hi>Turks,</hi> far superiour in number. And it's credibly believed; had the <hi>Germans</hi> charged the Enemy, at the same time
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:199106:26"/> that Prodigious Army of Infidels, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting to no less then 250000 Horse and Foot, had easily been defeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but the cold temper of <hi>Montecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culy,</hi> would not permit him to venture further. The <hi>French,</hi> since that time have been continually in action in <hi>France, Germany, Spain, Flanders</hi> or <hi>Holland,</hi> and by Sea likewise, as well as by Land; So that we may reckon them now the best trained up Souldiers <hi>Europe</hi> affords. Their main strength consists in a considerable number of old and experienced Officers, capable of any Military employment. But their present greatness, they chiefly ow to the Grand Genius of their Prince, which renders him equally fit for Politick and Warlike affairs. The never interrupted current of his Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, seems to render all things possible to him, his numerous standing Forces, and infinite Treasures, furnish him with all conveniencies either to defend himself, or attack his Enemies. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides he counts near twenty Millions of Souls in his Dominions, whereof five may be reckoned fighting Men, and fit to carry Arms.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:199106:26"/>
            <p>Out of which, without a very vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible diminution of the Number of his Subjects, he may draw in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Body Two hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand good Souldiers. And I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in this present instant he has a hundred thousand Men on foot in pay. <hi>France</hi> seems yet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another account inexpugnable. 'Tis surrounded, on all sides by the best fortified holds in <hi>Europe:</hi> For the <hi>French</hi> excel in this age, all their Neighbours in the Art of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying. They threaten all <hi>Italy</hi> with <hi>Pinerol,</hi> and <hi>Casal,</hi> that they are lately possessed of. <hi>Pirpignan</hi> makes them terrible to the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,</hi> and all the World knows what strong Citys they possess now in the <hi>Low</hi> Countrys; such as <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, Cambray, Valenciens Aire,</hi> St. <hi>Omers, Conde, Bouching, Dinant, Charle-Roy,</hi> &amp;c. but towards <hi>Germany;</hi> especially the <hi>French</hi> seem Invincible. They are in possession of the <hi>Franch</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and of his strong Holds, as <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sancone, Gray, Saling, Dole,</hi> of <hi>Alsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:199106:27"/> and Towns of no less renown for being well fortified. Then <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sac, Friburg</hi> in <hi>Brisgo, Stestadt, Strasburg, Marsal, Nancy, Metz, Longuy,</hi> &amp;c. which secure the <hi>French</hi> from any foraign irruption: And may back with advantage their Armies, breaking in upon <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we have taken a short view of the <hi>French Puissance.</hi> Yet are not of Opinion that all this, or more would be sufficient, to stop the progress of the <hi>Turkish</hi> Forces, if their attempts had proved so successful, as to have taken <hi>Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi> For though the <hi>French</hi> be no less Potent, then I have said be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, yet I any confident they are inferiour in strength to the <hi>Turks,</hi> because the Grand Signior▪ posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth such vast Territories, that he is able to set on foot thrice as meny men, as <hi>France:</hi> And has constantly under Pay, Fifty or Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thousand men more. He can put to Sea, on an urgent occasion
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:199106:27"/> Six hundred Sail; counting Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lys, and great Ships: Besides, what the Coast of <hi>Barbary</hi> can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford him. <hi>Egypt</hi> at any time, may furnish his Armies, with For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thousand Men fit for Service, and inured to hardship. <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the adjacent Provinces may supply him with a greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: It being a great mistake to say that his Territories lie waste, and are not populous. <hi>Asia Minor,</hi> or the Lesser <hi>Asia,</hi> that is now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely in his possession, is as full of People, as ever it was. <hi>Smyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> is very populous; and <hi>Aleppo</hi> counts within its Walls Thirty thousand fighting Men. <hi>Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> its advantagious situation being more convenient and suita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for so great a Monarchy, then any other City of the known World, has its Number of Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants answerable to its vast ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. The <hi>Islands</hi> of the <hi>Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean</hi> Sea, are as full as an Egg. And though <hi>Graecia</hi> be not near so flourishing now, as it was of old;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:199106:28"/> yet 'tis like a Seminary of stout Men, for the Grand Signior's Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. From <hi>Constantinople,</hi> to <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> the <hi>Turkish</hi> Citys are both frequent, and populous. His Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries are his choicest Men, being train'd up from their tender years, in all Military Discipline; these are the support of that Monarchy, and form a Body of Foot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly Forty thousand strong. His Horse are the <hi>Spahis,</hi> whereof he had in his Army before <hi>Vienna</hi> Fifty thousand, and more, are his Choicest Horse. He may set on foot on extraordinary occasion, Six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thousand fighting Men; which no two Christian Princes can do jointly, much less severally. The Grand Signior has in bulk enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his Empire by the Conquest of <hi>Candy,</hi> and almost all <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for his Treasures, they are very considerable, for he is the most absolute Monarch in the World, and disposeth Soveraignly,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:199106:28"/> of whatever his Subjects, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Slaves are possessed of. The Trading of <hi>Constantinople</hi> brings him in vast Summs of Money. He receives either a voluntary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cense or real Tribute from most of the <hi>Eastern</hi> States and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>The Christians, to get favour with the Grand Signior, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the promoting of their Trade with the Infidels, are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten at exceeding great, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times unwilling expences. For nothing is done at <hi>Constantinople,</hi> but by Money. And Money which is powerful every where is their Almighty. Now this Empire how can it be other then most dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to all Christendom, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider the great Magazines they have every where planted on the Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers of <hi>Germany,</hi> on the Confines of the <hi>Venetian</hi> Territories and all along the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> on the Coast of <hi>Barbary,</hi> &amp;c. from whence they may draw whatever is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:199106:29"/> for supplying of their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, either for the Besieging of Towns, or keeping the Mastery of the Field, in order to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest or Desolation of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; and as for the Souldiers, they may be as good, (to say no more) as our best <hi>Europeans.</hi> They are naturally resolute, of an undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Courage, and more Zealous to fight for their Religion, then Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians themselves. Their Captains understand all the Stratagems of War, as well, if not better then the most experienced Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians. There is no War like that of Machines, as <hi>Bombs, Grenades, Red Bullets, Carcasses,</hi> &amp;c. which they have as well as we, and can make use of 'em to the best ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. No Men in the World, understand better, the Art of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, whereof they gave good proof in the famous Siege of <hi>Candia,</hi> and lately in that of <hi>Vienna.</hi> This is their most efficacious and surest Method of making strong Cities submit; they were more
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:199106:29"/> troublesome to the Garison of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna,</hi> by their Mines, then by their Cannon, though therein they did their part. Now if the <hi>Turks,</hi> so well provided both with Men and all other Necessaries for great Enterprizes, had either by Surrender or Force taken <hi>Vienna,</hi> what Confusion would the Affairs of <hi>Germany;</hi> Yea, and <hi>France</hi> too been in? For the Sea thus let in, would not have been so easily thrust back again.</p>
            <p>Betwixt <hi>Vienna,</hi> and the <hi>Rhine;</hi> you have no City of any consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable strength; but weakly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, and unfit to stop a victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Army. The Princes of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> in this Juncture of Affairs, would be forc'd to give free pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage to the Enemy, or join with him as his Friends, and Allies, which several, I doubt would not have scrupled, as having less ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred for the <hi>Turks,</hi> then the <hi>French</hi> King. Would not <hi>France</hi> then have some Reason to fear the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:199106:30"/>
               <hi>Turbant,</hi> as being back'd by a part of <hi>Germany</hi> it self, and perhaps the strongest, who either by fear, or hopes, might all, or most, be forced or encouraged to follow the fortune of the Conquerour. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over the Neighbourhood of the <hi>Turks,</hi> for I see not what could hinder their progress from <hi>Vienna,</hi> to <hi>Strasburg,</hi> would soon stir up all the Malecontents of <hi>France,</hi> who are now in greater Numbers, then ever, to join with them against their Prince, wherein not only open, but secret ways would be found of betraying and lessening his Interests, and informing the Enemy of whatever would be of any consequence for his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern. <hi>Friburg</hi> in <hi>Brisgo, Brisac, Slestadt, Strasburg,</hi> and all the other strong Holds of <hi>Alsatia</hi> might indeed stay the <hi>Turkish</hi> Troops a while, but not quite stop their progress. Open force I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess would not prevail much against <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> and <hi>Brisac,</hi> but there is no City so strong, but hunger
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:199106:30"/> may Conquer. The Grand Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior in such a case having behind him the fertilest Countrys of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> could neither want Victuals, nor other Necessary Provisions for his Armies, and these being in this Conjuncture, if ever, very nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, he could easily be Master of the Fields and Plains of <hi>Alsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia;</hi> by laying over the <hi>Rhine,</hi> a Bridge or two of Boats, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying them on each side, to the best advantage. Which done, if the <hi>French</hi> would not venture a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, which would be of a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Consequence, in this situation of Affairs, they would either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat towards <hi>Lorrain,</hi> by <hi>Stras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg:</hi> Or the <hi>Franch</hi> County by <hi>Ensesem,</hi> or shut themselves up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the strong holds they have in these parts, in hopes to ruine, or at least to weaken the <hi>Turkish</hi> Forces, before they came to a pitcht Battel. And in this case, the strongest Citys of <hi>Alsatia,</hi> would be forced at length to sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render by Famine, how well so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:199106:31"/> they might be provided, in the beginning. For with two fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Armies, the <hi>Turks</hi> could easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly stop the Narrow passages into <hi>Alsatia,</hi> from the <hi>Franch</hi> County, and from <hi>Lorrain</hi> by <hi>Mulsem.</hi> The neglect whereof, in the late Wars against the <hi>French,</hi> was the sole cause that <hi>Brisac,</hi> and all <hi>Alsatia</hi> escaped the <hi>Germans.</hi> For the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quess</hi> of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> against the late Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi>'s advice, having sent too few Forces to keep the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per passage, from the <hi>Franch</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: <hi>Turene</hi> forced it with no great loss, and so broke into the Plains of <hi>Alsatia,</hi> resolved to fight the <hi>Germans.</hi> But the Marquess of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg,</hi> by reason of the <hi>Sweeds,</hi> at that very Nick of time Rava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging his Country, after a rude Skirmish, retreated prudently, in good order with his Baggage, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, and all the <hi>German</hi> Forces, except a considerable Number of Sick-men, that were left up, and down in the Villages, as likewise at <hi>Slestadt, Colmar,</hi> and <hi>Than. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satia</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:199106:31"/> once Conquered, either by the Valour of the <hi>Turks,</hi> or by their Number, <hi>Lorrain</hi> and the <hi>Franch</hi> County would be forced to sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render, after the same manner; as the <hi>Turks</hi> might keep the Fields, with an Army strong enough to Oppose the <hi>French,</hi> and Block up, or Besiege the strong Holds with another. If these three Provinces, I mean, the <hi>Franch</hi> County, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satia,</hi> and <hi>Lorrain,</hi> fell into the <hi>Turks</hi> hands, as in all likelihood they would; the whole fortune of <hi>France</hi> would lie at the Stake. For in this case, it would be an abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Necessity, to come to a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral decision by the Sword, there being no strong Towns, between the Frontier Citys, and <hi>Paris.</hi> And the <hi>Turks</hi> being not only terrible in Battel, by their Number, but likewise by their Valour, and dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity, 'tis but a Childish Vanity in the <hi>French</hi> to boast, and to say, that if they were their Neighbours, they would easily overthrow 'em and thrust 'em out of <hi>Europe.</hi> For
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:199106:32"/> these Infidels, would perhaps give them as much, and more ado, then now to the <hi>Germans,</hi> though 'tis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, they might be somewhat more successful, because of their subjection to one absolute Prince; who having no Man's particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, or Inclinations to manage, might dispose of his Forces, when, and in what manner, he thought fittest. Neither do I as yet see, what help in such an extream Necessity, <hi>France</hi> could expect from its Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. For being hated by them all, as having at some time, or other, been troublesome to 'em all, who knows whether they would be so forward, as to lend them an helping hand against the Infidels? What the Concerns of <hi>Holland</hi> would be in the Case, cannot be judged, but at the Instant, and will be guided by the Popular Air of hatred, or love; and according to the prevalency of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther its measures may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:199106:32"/>
            <p>As to Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> as it fears no body, so it might not seem to have so near a Concern for the <hi>Turks</hi> Success in <hi>France.</hi> For as <hi>France</hi> is the only Kingdom in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> it looks upon with a jealous Eye 'tis a Topick of the, Time not to be much dissatisfied with what may eclipse that Monarch's Glory and Grandure. The <hi>Spaniards,</hi> 'tis presumed, and the <hi>Italians,</hi> wou'd lend them their helping hand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of the Profession of the same Religion: yet how far that might touch <hi>Spain</hi> I begin to doubt again, especially whether the <hi>Spanish</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks wou'd not teach them in this Conjuncture to lay aside for a while their pretended Zeal for Religion, whenever they judge it separable from their temporal Interest: which might well happen in this Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, the Humiliation of the <hi>French,</hi> by whosoever it happens, being their greatest Advantage. As to the <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians,</hi> they could do but little with their Temporal Swords; but if pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises of Myriads of Pardons, Jubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:199106:33"/> and Indulgencies, will stir up the rest of Christendom to its own Defence, 'twould be a happy Point gained, and they might come in for their share: but the <hi>Turks</hi> would not regard all this; and perhaps the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of <hi>Romanists</hi> seeing the great Success of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, would not much hearken to such Exhortations. Another thing yet would deject the <hi>French,</hi> in this suppos'd Juncture of Affairs; which is, the unheard of Cruelty of the <hi>Turks</hi> in their Conquests, their chief Policy consisting in terrifying their Enemies from a lawful Defence, by most barbarous Cruelties us'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst such as do their duty in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of their Trust and Country. So 'tis credibly reported, that the <hi>Grand Visier</hi> had resolv'd to put to the Sword not the Garrison only of <hi>Vienna,</hi> but indifferently all, Men, Women, Young, and Old, without having regard, either to Age, or Sex. That Incomparable General <hi>Starremberg,</hi> to whom <hi>Germany,</hi> and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:199106:33"/> all Christendom is so peeuliarly obliged, was to be put to death, with exquisite torments. Some of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners assured, the Grand Visier would have caused his Hands, and Feet to be cut off, and the Blood to be stopt, that so he might starve to death: Not so much thorow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particular hatred, conceived a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this great Man, for I am confident he could not but have a great Esteem, and respect for him, although an Enemy, because of his good Conduct, and vigorous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, but through a special piece of Policy, to give an example, and terrour to the rest of <hi>Germany;</hi> that the other Governours frigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by such extream Rigours, might the more easily yield up the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tys, and holds committed to their Trust. The like Rigour undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, and for the same reason, they would use in the case we have supposed. Which would prove the shortest, and most Effleacious way, to make a Considerable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:199106:34"/> in the <hi>French</hi> Dominions; for then the Governours of strong Towns, considering what quarter, or rather what barbarous usage they were to expect, in case of resistance, would for the most part comply with the Enemy and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray their Prince, not through fear of Death that's undetermined, which would be little regarded by a generous Heart, but to shun these extream Rigours design'd in cool Blood capable to shake, I may so say, Constancy it self, and the strongest Courage.</p>
            <p>From all this, we may conclude, that 'tis the main Interest (if we will consider things Impartially) of <hi>France,</hi> as well as <hi>Germany, Spain,</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> and all the other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to oppose the <hi>Turks</hi> in time▪ and hinder their progress in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many.</hi> For tho' perhaps <hi>France</hi> might at first feem greater, by the Fall of the most Illustrious House of <hi>Austria:</hi> Yet this greatness
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:199106:34"/> in all likelihood would not prove very lasting, because of the <hi>Turks</hi> hatred against all Christians; and more espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially against the <hi>French,</hi> there being a sort of Tradition amongst these Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, that a <hi>French</hi> King shall destroy their Monarchy, which I would not have the <hi>French</hi> to trust to, as if it were a true Prophecy; since it may, for ought I know, be rather coyn'd in <hi>France,</hi> than in <hi>Turkey.</hi> I doubt not indeed, if that ought to make the <hi>French</hi> less interested for the rest, but that the Infidels, if they had had suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess in <hi>Germany,</hi> would, before all things, have ratified a solid Truce with the <hi>French,</hi> as most capable to do them mischief; but this had been but for a while, and for their own ends, to ferve first their Conquests, or put themselves into a better Posture to attacque afterwards the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I come to give you an exact and true Account of all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of the Late Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> such as has not been as yet given to the publick. I must speak one word to the Concerns of <hi>Holland,</hi> allowing
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:199106:35"/> the supposition of <hi>Vienna</hi>'s being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the <hi>Turks;</hi> the States of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> had no doubt been under the same condition with the rest of <hi>Germany,</hi> where many of the <hi>German</hi> Princes, if not all, would have rather been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to redeem the possession of their Territories, by paying a yearly Tribute, than run the hazard of losing all by an unequal War. The <hi>Hollanders</hi> could not expect much better Terms, for either they would have been forc'd to comply after the same manner, or undertake a War against a too power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Enemy, and with danger of being Conquer'd. The little resistance they made against the <hi>French,</hi> in 1672. gives us not reason to expect great things from them, in such a conjuncture; their greatest Strength being by Sea, and not by Land. But I am very apt to believe they would agree with the <hi>Turk</hi> at any rate, if not lend him also a help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hand: Their own weakness, and the advantage of their <hi>Constantinopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litan</hi> Trade, engaging them to accept of any Conditions.</p>
            <p>We have seen hitherto the disadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:199106:35"/> and the fatal consequences would have attended the loss of <hi>Vienna;</hi> let us now take a short view of the great advantages and benefit gain'd by the conservation of this Imperial City, and overthrow of the <hi>Turks</hi> before it. First <hi>Italy,</hi> &amp; especially the State of <hi>Venice,</hi> becomes freed of a too well ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fear, of becoming a prey to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels. The Kingdom of <hi>Poland</hi> may hope for the recovery of <hi>Kaminieck,</hi> and pretend to further Conquests upon the <hi>Turks,</hi> by the help of the <hi>Zapora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Cossocks.</hi> The House of <hi>Austria,</hi> together with all <hi>Germany,</hi> are freed from a present danger of being entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ruin'd; for the Empire in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture was hardly put to it, and in a manner betwixt the Hammer and the Anvil. The <hi>Turks</hi> did attacque the <hi>Germans</hi> on the one side, the <hi>French</hi> King threatned them on the other, and, which was worst of all, they were not in a good Correspondency together, because of the Intrigues of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and some particular Princes pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate concerns. <hi>France</hi> made not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed an open War against the Empire,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:199106:36"/> but, which was rather worse than bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, kept a strong Army upon the Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers of <hi>Germany,</hi> which held the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> in the <hi>French</hi> Interest. Yea the rumour was, that the <hi>French</hi> King had a hand in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the <hi>Turks</hi> into <hi>Germany,</hi> and that his Ambassador <hi>Monsieur De Vitry</hi> in <hi>Poland,</hi> did what lay in his power to hinder the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> from concluding an Offensive and Defensive League with the Emperour, against the <hi>Turk,</hi> their common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; and seeing he could not prevail, wrought s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>tly upon some of the Grande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>land,</hi> to revolt against their Prince in his absence: Which are all things so far beneath the pretences of a most Christian Prince, that they must be extraordinarily well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ackt to gain a belief; especially since h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s known generosity and zeal against the <hi>Turks</hi> hath appear'd to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary at <hi>Candy,</hi> and before in <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry▪</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e conjuncture I spoke of else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; and therefore unless herein In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> hath prevail'd, which I take not on me to judg, 'twill be a piece
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:199106:36"/> of injustice to believe all such reports. However, 'tis certain, as to the <hi>French</hi> themselves, that they seem to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no less concern'd at the bad success of the <hi>Turks,</hi> than if they were really Subjects to the Grand Signior; which comes not from any kindness they have for the <hi>Turk,</hi> but out of love they bear to the honour of their own Prince; whose measures they think somewhat shorten'd by this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected overthrow of the▪ <hi>Ottoman</hi> Forces, as undoubtedly they are; for, whatever was that Princes aim, whether to be chosen Emperour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, the present Emperour renouncing the Empire, as some Princes have done, in such an extreme distress; or whether he design'd in the situation of Affairs to attacque <hi>Germany, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or the <hi>Low Countrys,</hi> 'tis not so well known; but 'tis certain he has met with a no small disappointment, at least for some considerable time yet, as to all these designs, if in truth they ever really were in being.</p>
            <p>But now, as the Emperour by this great Victory, is become more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:199106:37"/> than he was in <hi>Germany;</hi> yea and more terrible likewise to those that would raise stirs against him there: So the number of his Friends will in all appearance en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, with his good Fortune, and that of his Enemies decrease. He is moreover in a fitter posture now than ever, to tye the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> together, in an Offensive and Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive League, against the common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Empire, whoever they be, either <hi>Turks</hi> or <hi>Christians.</hi> And the <hi>German</hi> Princes that were waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Emperour's side, find it now their Interest to joyn hands with him again. will stand no longer off, but by complying prevent their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over run by the <hi>Turks,</hi> or becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Subjects to the <hi>French</hi> Monarch. <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> were never in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion either to resist, or oppose <hi>France,</hi> without the help of <hi>Germany,</hi> which now they may hope for, since the <hi>Turks</hi> by a special Providence of God over Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tendom, have got such a Wound at <hi>Vienna,</hi> as will not cure in hast. Upon this account Bon-fires are made all
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:199106:37"/> over <hi>Germany,</hi> and in the Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, especially in token of their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream joy for this good success, for that they looked upon this great Victory as gained against the <hi>French,</hi> whom they take to be Instrumental to the present desolation of <hi>Germany,</hi> and their most dangerous Enemies, as having more reason to fear them than the <hi>Turks.</hi> The <hi>Germans</hi> have once already rescued the Low Countries from the <hi>French,</hi> and their Heavy Yoak, and if not at present, yet so soon as a firm Peace or Truce is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with the Grand Signiour may be in a capacity to preserve them for the time to come.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>England,</hi> tho' it makes a world apart, and seems little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd either in the advantage, or disad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the <hi>German</hi> Empire, yet all His Majesties Subjects that have a due Sense, and are willing to understand their own True Interest, may look upon this Victory of the Christian Forces in <hi>Germany,</hi> as indirectly le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled against their most powerful, and most dangerous Rival, the <hi>French;</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:199106:38"/> who in this age, under the Auspicious Reign of <hi>Lewis the Great,</hi> are come to such a pitch of Grandeur, that they have conceived some hopes to be Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters one Day of <hi>Europe,</hi> none of their Neighbours being at present (<hi>England</hi> excepted) an equal Match for 'em. The Chamber called <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Reunion</hi> established at <hi>Metz</hi> by the <hi>French</hi> Kings Command, discovers clearly a Design of an Universal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy. Whatever this Chamber de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares to belong directly, or indirectly to any City, or Village possess'd by the French King, whether it be in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> or <hi>Flanders,</hi> 'tis first required as a thing due, and in case of refusal seis'd upon instantly by force. If the <hi>French</hi> were not already in a posture to Master the most part of their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; the <hi>Reunion Chamber</hi> as they call it, had never presumed to decide Pretensions so Sovereignly in favour of the <hi>French</hi> King. For such Decrees without a Power able to put 'em in Execution, had been laught at, and look'd upon as an elevated piece of folly. Since the famous Battel of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croy,</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:199106:38"/> where the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> gave a total overthrow to the best Troops that ever <hi>Spain</hi> set on Foot, the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish</hi> Monarchy hath so visibly decay'd, that there is no Nation in <hi>Europe</hi> this Day less seared by its Neighbours than <hi>Spain. Portugal</hi> alone almost over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matehed it. No wonder then, if the <hi>Spaniards</hi> be overpowered by the <hi>French,</hi> now stronger than ever. The divisions of <hi>Germany</hi> do promote ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly the <hi>French</hi> Interest, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>German</hi> Princes much less ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible then they would be, if well uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted together, <hi>England</hi> only seems to be without the reach of the <hi>French,</hi> because of its Natural Situation, and its Invincible Strength, being not only se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the rest of the World by the Sea; <hi>Et penitus toto divisos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orbe Britannos;</hi> but besides having within themselves all Necessaries, either for their own defence, or att<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cquing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. The <hi>English</hi> are the absolute Masters of the Seas, and by reason of their daring Humour, and little valuing of their lives, the fittest Men in the World for a Sea Combat: What
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:199106:39"/> they can do by Land every one knows The <hi>French</hi> have all reason to be kind to 'em, for the good Service they render'd him in the late Wars a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>Germans.</hi> I may say with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Exaggeration, they saved together with the <hi>Scots</hi> nothing inferior to 'em in Courage, and more inur'd to Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, the Kingdom of <hi>France</hi> perhaps from its utter destruction: For had the <hi>Germans</hi> broke into <hi>France</hi> by <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satia</hi> and <hi>Lorraign,</hi> the Conquest of <hi>Campagne</hi> had been an easy matter; the <hi>French</hi> Forces being too much bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sied in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and elsewere to come to relieve it. The Earl of <hi>Dumbar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> with the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects got the honour of the first Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, obtained against the Duke of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign</hi> and <hi>Caparara,</hi> not far from the <hi>Rhine</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> The <hi>French</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valry was beaten back by the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and the Cannon to the number of ten taken, which the <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>English</hi> Foot regain'd, with their Swords in their Hands, and a great slaughter of the Enemies. Near <hi>Stratsburg</hi> they had the good luck to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:199106:39"/> take from the <hi>Germans</hi> after an obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Combat, Ten Field-pieces, and a great many Colours. In the Battel of <hi>Colmar</hi> against the Marquess of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg, Turin</hi> gave them deservedly all the honour of the Day, and in the Action that happened after <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rins</hi> Death, between the <hi>German</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> Army, they withstood with all imaginable courage, the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Cavalry, and gave time to the Army to retreat, without any conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable loss. But besides the advantage of the best Men <hi>Europe</hi> affords, <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is a Rich and Plentiful Countrey, and wants not Money (by reason of its great Trading) sufficient for the maintaining of a considerable War.</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding all this, it has rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to be Jealous of the <hi>French,</hi> and to look upon them as its most dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Neighbours. <hi>Englands</hi> True Interest then requires that some limits be set to the growing <hi>Puissance</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> Empire; which cannot be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily done Without the help of the <hi>Germans,</hi> against whom if the <hi>Turks</hi> had prevailed, <hi>England</hi> thorow a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:199106:40"/> principle of self preservation, had been oblige<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with unequal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rces, as to the number to defend the Low Countries, and <hi>Holland</hi> from a <hi>French</hi> Invasion. The <hi>French</hi> now will be forced to take New Measures, and being some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what affrighted at the good Success of the <hi>Germans</hi> against the <hi>Turks,</hi> will not so easily ingage in a War against the <hi>Spanish</hi> Territories, in the Low Countries, lest they should be Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on the other side by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in case a Peace were concluded with the <hi>Turk;</hi> which may be easily obtained by reason of the great over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw they have got before <hi>Vienna Englands</hi> advantage then in this juncture of Affairs, consists in this, That the <hi>French</hi> hereafter shall not be in a capacity to undertake War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>England;</hi> the <hi>Germans</hi> once freed from the <hi>Turks,</hi> being always in a readiness to joyn with us, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade <hi>France.</hi> I confess indeed the strength of <hi>Great Britain</hi> once uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is so considerable, that though <hi>France</hi> had conquered <hi>Holland,</hi> and the <hi>Spanish</hi> Low Countries, it could not
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:199106:40"/> for all this prevail against <hi>England,</hi> by open force. Yet in such a case the <hi>Hollanders</hi> being subject to the <hi>French,</hi> would receive so great an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of power by Sea, that in few years the <hi>English</hi> Trade might nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly decay, though perhaps the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary might well happen, the <hi>English</hi> being attackt at Sea, for both the <hi>French</hi> and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. But in this Neighbourhood of the <hi>French,</hi> nothing would more prejudice <hi>England</hi> than their Emissa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and Pensioners, who would not fail to cut the Nation by their secret Intrigues, into different Factions, and so render it less capable of a vigorous Defence. For I conceive not what else could ruine <hi>Great Britain,</hi> but <hi>Great Britain</hi> it self. If then the <hi>French</hi> may now, and perhaps do cast the <hi>Apple</hi> of Discord amongst us, they would no doubt succeed better in this Design, in such a Conjuncture of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs: which we need not as yet fear as if it were at hand. Since in all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood, the <hi>Turks</hi> will not be in a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to busie all <hi>Germany</hi> hereafter,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:199106:41"/> if the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour stand to the League, concluded betwixt them, for their mutual de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, or rather we may hope that these Infidels will change now their last years Fortune, and beg humbly a Truce, which they had refused not long ago so fiercely, with the hopes of no less than the Conquest of the <hi>German</hi> Empire, which Truce or Peace could not but prove fatal to <hi>France,</hi> if the Emperour turned his Armies, which in all likelyhood he would do, against the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I shall now to give a full satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Readers Curiosity, set down a true and most exact account of all the Remarkable Passages of the late Siege of <hi>Vienna</hi> which gave occasion to the foregoing Discourses. I had this Journal from an Officer of the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison, of my old acquaintance, a very Ingenious Man, and a good Scholar, I shall but English his words.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:199106:41"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199106:42"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199106:42"/>
            <head>An Impartial and true Account, of all the most considerable Passages and Actions relating to the Siege of the Imperial City <hi>VIENNA;</hi> being the Memoirs of a considerable Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer of that Garison, who was actually in Service there till the Siege was rais'd. Which he thus relates:</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Anno 1683.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Seventh of <hi>July</hi> in the Forenoon we had a hot Alarm, at the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival here of the Count of <hi>Stirum,</hi> who desired his Imperial Majesty to send a speedy supply of Men to the Army, as being much inferior to the Enemies in Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and upon that account, unable
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199106:43"/> to stop their progress: But our fears were exceedingly increased by the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon, when the Count of <hi>Caprara</hi> came hither to inform the Emperor of the near approach of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and to desire him, without any further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, to remove from thence with the Arch-Duke, the Enemy being not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly stronger than was at first reported, but reinforc'd by a considerable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Rebels and <hi>Tartars;</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly in the Evening the Emperor parted from <hi>Vienna</hi> for <hi>Clooster New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> intending to go from thence to <hi>Lintz.</hi> The same day the Boors came hither in great numbers, flying from all parts, by reason of the cruelties of the <hi>Turkish</hi> Army, against all such as they met with in their passage.</p>
            <p>The day after, in the Morning ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived here our Cavalry, having left the Infantry in the Island of <hi>Schutz,</hi> after their Retreat; or rather Flight from before the <hi>Turkish</hi> Army. We were not hitherto certain whether the <hi>Turks</hi> design'd the Siege of <hi>Vienna</hi> or not: And some were of opinion there, was no such design on Foot, because of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:199106:43"/> the resistance the <hi>Turks</hi> would expect to meet withal from an Imperial City, and the union of all the <hi>German</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which such an important occasion would in all likelihood effect. But soon after we were clear'd of this doubt, by the arrival of Count <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remberg,</hi> and General <hi>Capeliers,</hi> sent by the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in chief, with Twelve thousand Men out of the Army to strengthen the Garison.</p>
            <p>The very next day after, the whole <hi>Turkish</hi> Army appeared within a <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> League of <hi>Vienna,</hi> consisting of One hundred and fifty thousand Fighting Men Horse and Foot, Commanded by the Grand Vizier in Person; with se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral considerable <hi>Bassa</hi>'s, and the best Officers and Soldiers of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire. The Consternation of the Citizens at the first sight of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious Army cannot be expressed; but Count <hi>Staremberg</hi> showing a chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful countenance, and little fear of this vast multitude, did somewhat incour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age the people.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:199106:44"/>
            <p>The <hi>Ottomen</hi> Forces being now with in Cannon-Shot of our Out-works made a Halt for a while, to take, as it were, a view of the scituation of the place; they made several Detachments of Horse and Foot, to seize upon all the Avenues and the cheif Passages to the City. In the mean time Count <hi>Staremberg</hi> having drawn out the greatest part of the Garison, sent at the instant against some Squadrons that came too near the Out-works, about Five hundred <hi>Dragoons,</hi> who beat the <hi>Turks</hi> back, with the loss of Seven men only.</p>
            <p>That whole Night the Enemies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook nothing; but alighting from their Horses, remained without any noise. Our Men in the mean while lying close in the Ravelins, Redoubts, and along the <hi>Chemincovert.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the break of day we heard the Trumpets Sound from all parts of their Camp, which occasion'd a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of people towards the Walls of the City, and was looked upon by some as a forerunner of some enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize: But all this noise was nothing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:199106:44"/> else but an usual Ceremony amongst the <hi>Turks,</hi> when the Grand Vizier is to go first to his Quarters before a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieged Town; which he took the same day at the Palace of the Empress Dowager, called <hi>La Favorita.</hi> His Camp then appeared in all its glory, extended as far as <hi>Nusdorps.</hi> The Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages were without number; the Cannon amounted to several Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of all sorts: Their Tents were most magnificent, to the number of Thirty thousand and more.</p>
            <p>Their first attempt was upon <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polestadt;</hi> it was defended by a Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Dragoons,</hi> and two of Foot, who did their Duty to a Miracle. The <hi>Turks</hi> were thrice beat out of it, after they had almost master'd it by their great numbers. <hi>Staremberg</hi> well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Leopolestadt</hi> being an open place, could not hold out against this Power, and desirous to manage his men for more necessary occasions, ordered the Officers that Commanded there, to destroy as much as they could thereof, by firing the same, that so it might prove useless to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:199106:45"/>
               <hi>Turks;</hi> which they performed, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the great oppositions of the <hi>Janizaries,</hi> of whom, but more especially of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> a great slaughter was made on that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</p>
            <p>The Troops then that had defended <hi>Leopolestadt</hi> so bravely, withdrew to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Bridge, but were followed closely by the Enemies, and suffered some loss, because they could not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily Face about; but herein not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable. They Retreated then into the City, carrying along with them about Five an thirty wounded Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Soldiers, as likewise the dead Bodies of some persons of Note, that had signalized their Courage in that Service.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Staremberg</hi> took a view of these Forces at their return, praised the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers for their good Behaviour, with promise in time and place, to move for a proportionable Reward from his Emperial Majesty. About this time the Count <hi>Serini,</hi> having Revolted from the Emperor, and joyned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self with a Body of Eight thousand
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:199106:45"/>
               <hi>Tartars,</hi> was Attacked by General <hi>Dunwalt</hi> in the Woods not far from us, defeated, and himself taken Prisoner, besides a great number of <hi>Tarters</hi> slain on the spot. But of such things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I have not been Eye Witness I shall say the less; I shall chiefly concern my self in this short and plain Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, communicating what I have either seen, or could not but know, being at my turn an Actor in most of these our most important exploits.</p>
            <p>Count <hi>Staremberg</hi> considering the importance of his Trust, and the fatal consequences to the whole Christian World (should <hi>Vienna</hi> be taken by the Infidels) had a watchful eye on all sides, either to take an advantage of the Enemy, or surprise them, which he did often, as well as render unsuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessful their Attacks. By this time the Citizens had recovered themselves from their first amazement, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning now to look the Enemies in the Face with an undaunted Courage, conceived some hopes of a good suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess: But nothing incouraged them more than the trust they had in their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199106:46"/> Governor the Count of <hi>Staremberg</hi> who took little rest by Day or by Night, and gave as little to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>They first began the Siege, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out keeping the ordinary forms, as not knowing yet how strong our Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison was. And in this method, to the number of Thirty thousand Horse and Foot, they March'd on a suddain from all sides, towards our out-works, causing the Neighbouring Valleys, and Hills, to rebound with their shouts. Which mistake of theirs being taken notice of by <hi>Staremberg,</hi> without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther delay, he Commanded the whole Garison within the Walls to be in a readiness, the rest being at their Post without to receive the Enemy; which they did with great success, by the incouragement and good example of their Officers, more especially of their Governor. For the <hi>Turks</hi> were every where repulsed with great loss, which made them somewhat more sober, and less daring.</p>
            <p>After this great Action, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the third day after the arrival
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:199106:46"/> of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Forces before <hi>Vienna, Staremberg</hi> caus'd an exact account to be taken of all the Provisions that were in the Magazines, and was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways present himself at their distribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion among the Soldiers, as well as Scholars and younger Brothers that Mounted the Guard. An Oath like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise was by him Administred to them, to defend the place to the last, and never to hearken to any Proposals from the Enemy, how advantagious soever they might be. So that now the Siege went on on both sides ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the usual forms, the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies finding it otherwise impossible to gain the City; after the advices given by their Spies of the Strength and Resolution of the Garison and Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens.</p>
            <p>To annoy us with their great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillary, which was chiefly managed by Renegadoes, they set up several Batteries, which gave us little rest ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by day or night, though they had little other effect at that time, than the dismounting of two or three pieces of Cannon, and the Killing of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:199106:47"/> some Centinels. The <hi>Turks</hi> made three considerable Attacks near the <hi>Scotembourg Gate</hi> and the <hi>Red Tower,</hi> but were as often beat off, with the loss of more than Six thousand men slain on the place; besides Prisoners, among whom some were of considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble quallity.</p>
            <p>In regard this Action resulted so much to the honour of our Party, I will give you a particular account thereof. The <hi>Turks</hi> having with their Cannon demolished some considerable parts of the Fortifications towards the <hi>Scots Gate</hi> and the <hi>Red Tower,</hi> did the day before prepare for a general Attack on that side, Lying quiet for the space of Six hours, in which time they drew their Cannon and Gabions nearer. But <hi>Staremberg</hi> mistrusting this unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected calm, judg'd aright, That it was a mark of some great actions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed by the <hi>Turks:</hi> And therefore Commanded out towards that side One thousand six hundred Men, to joyn with those that were almost at handy-blows with the Enemy. In prosecution whereof fell out this acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:199106:47"/> that gave some disturbance to the Sally out: Two of the chief Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders quarrelled about the Post, each of them pretending to the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, and the greatest Honour, with the greatest danger. <hi>Staremberg</hi> soon informed of their strife, came out him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self and composed the difference, giving on the side of Right the favour of his Judgement, yet not without a sharp reproof to them both for such unseasonable disputes, the example whereof would be of a dangerous consequence. The emulation about the point of Honour thus terminated, this little Army resolutely went on against the <hi>Turks,</hi> who, after Three furious Discharges of the Artillery, came on most fiercely with their Swords in their Hands to assault the Christians; who had orders to be upon their Defence only, as being far inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in number to those that Attacked them. During the shock, the <hi>Turks</hi> were held busy on all the other sides of the City, both by small and great Shot, and some, though inconsidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sallies made out. This Attack
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:199106:48"/> of the <hi>Turks</hi> lasted a whole hour, and notwithstanding they were forced to a Retreat, they came on again with fresh Troops, the <hi>Bassa</hi> of <hi>Mesopotamia</hi> at their Head, but were worsted both times, with the loss of this <hi>Bassa,</hi> which they say, was mightily regret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>Turks,</hi> as being a Man of great Conduct and Valour: But the Enemy not discouraged, as yet, by this bad success, returned again about three in the Afternoon, with a greater number than before, continuing the Assault twice successively. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon a new supply was likewise sent out by the Governour, who thought it a business of a main concern, that we should defend our Posts. What part I had in this last Action I shall inform you; I was that Afternoon Commanded out with Count <hi>Leslie,</hi> who was killed in that Expedition. We had a considerable loss in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this last Shock, by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merity of some overventuring Officers: But the <hi>Turks</hi> coming on us somewhat in a confusion, and we waiting for them in a great calm, our Files being
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:199106:48"/> at such a reasonable distance the ground woud permit, and in good Order, they were repulsed again, with the loss of a considerable Body of Men, wherein our Soldiers Firing so punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally at Command, in short time we got the better of them, and forced them to a shameful Retreat. In this Action were killed more than Two thousand Men; and in the whole day Four thousand more; whose heaps to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether lay about the same place where they fought.</p>
            <p>This Mortality being taken notice of by the Grand Vizier, and fearing lest the stink of their putrifying Bodies should infect the rest of his Army, he demanded a Cessation of Arms, whilst he gave Burial to his Dead; But the Count <hi>Staremberg's</hi> return was, That <hi>he had no need of a Truce, his Garison being all very well, and under no obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to gratify him therein.</hi> By which means the Dead were unburied; and it was the occasion of the Camps re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval from that side a little farther the following day, though they did not for this abandon their Attack.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:199106:49"/>
            <p>The Count <hi>Staremberg</hi> lay close for two days after this great Action, to give some rest to his Men, and take new measures. Neither did the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my attempt any thing more all that time; but yet was not idle, being busy working like Moles, both with their Hands and Feet, under the Ground.</p>
            <p>The first and only effect of their labour at this time, was the Blowing up of a Captain and near Fifty Soldiers, whereof some were only transported from that to another place, without being wounded. About Noon the same day we rendred them the like, by Springing a Mine that ruined one of their Batteries which had been the most of all troublesome to us, being so skilfully managed by an English Renegado. This done. a Sally out against the Enemy was ordered after this manner: The Trnmpets Sounded, the Drums, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Beat at the <hi>Scots</hi> Gate, and a considerable Party was sent out to draw the Enemy to that side, whilst by another Gate Eight hundred Foot were Marching in good Order; but
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:199106:49"/> withal, keeping a profound silence, till such time as they came near the Workers in the Trenches, on whom they fell so heartily, that in a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an Hour, and less, they put Four hundred and more to the Sword; but being discovered by a strong Party of <hi>Spahies,</hi> or <hi>Turkish</hi> Horse, they were forced to Retreat in some disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but with a small loss.</p>
            <p>The Grand Vizier in the mean time had several Ingineers at work under a Ravaline not far from the <hi>Lebel Basti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> they had advanced their Trench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es towards the Ravaline in two days time in such measure, that they had made themselves a passage into the Ditch; which the Officer that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded taking notice of, sends instant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an Express to inform the Governor of the imminent danger he was in, without a speedy and strong supply: But before the Express came back to give an answer, the Enemy had Sprung a Mine; the effect whereof, was the overthrow of the point of the Ravaline, and the loss of about Fifteen Soldiers and a Lieutenant. The <hi>Turks</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:199106:50"/> making their best advantage of this disorder, without any loss of time, came on furiously with their Swords in their Hands, they were at first re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulsed, and Retreated in great confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, carrying along with them the Body of the Officer that Commanded in this Action; who (as it was known afterwards) was Son to the <hi>Bassa</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor under the Grand Signior of <hi>Grand-Caire.</hi> The Enemies, as it may be presumed, under the apprehension of this accident, and for fear our num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in this interim might have been increased, would make no further at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt against the Ravaline: But their design in Retreating was only to see what would be the effect of another Mine they were to Spring near the entrance of the Ravaline, with intent, not only to hinder our men from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning into the City, but to put a stop to those that were expected to our assistance: Neither were they deceived in their expectations; for the Ravaline was intirely overturn'd into the Ditch that surrounded it, where most of those that had escaped the fury of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:199106:50"/> the first Attack, found their Burial places.</p>
            <p>I was eye-witness to this Action from a Flanking of a Bastion wherein I was on Duty; I judged the consequence of this misadventure could not but prove fatal to us, and had no good opinion at that time, of our good success in the Siege, because this ground gained upon us might facilitate the Enemies taking in of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terscarp, and consequently of the Ditch, which would give all imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conveniency to the <hi>Turks</hi> to Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine, and Blow up our Ramparts and Bastions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Staremberg</hi> at the first coming of the Express, had instantly ordered Five hundred choice Men, under the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of good Officers, to be in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diness; but as they were Drawing up, near the Great Church, the sad News came of this unhappy Relation: The consequence of which <hi>Staremberg</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever seemed not to value, prudently keeping a cheerful Countenance, as if he had feared nothing; but in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Commanded out Seven hundred
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:199106:51"/> Men more: They lost no time, but Marched altogether with that silence that was usually Commanded on such occasions, making such dispatch, that the Enemy had not got as yet leisure enough to lodge themselves on the Ravaline, but were forced to Face a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout upon our Men, without any great advantage from the Ground whereon they stood. They Fired briskly in the beginning, and beat us back, with a small loss on their side, and a considerable loss on ours: But having Rallied again, we entred the Ravaline▪ notwithstanding a showre of Small Shot from the <hi>Turks,</hi> and put them all to the Sword; yet all this was not enough to discourage them.</p>
            <p>They sprang the 18th of <hi>August</hi> another Mine under the same Ravaline, and entring the Breach, Attacked those that defended it, with Twelve hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred chosen Men; who were so well received by our Soldiers, that after having lost near Three hundred <hi>Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries,</hi> they were forced to quit the Breach, and got no other advantage
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:199106:51"/> that day, than to lodge themselves at the foot of the Ravaline.</p>
            <p>The next day about Ten a Clock in the Morning, Fifteen hundred fresh Men were sent to Relieve those that were in the Ravaline, much weakened by their continual Fatigue, having been near Eight and fourty hours up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hot Service: Their Order import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they should do their best at their first arrival, to dislodge the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my from the foot of the Ravaline; which they performed with such a resolution, and so good success, that the <hi>Turks</hi> could keep their Ground no longer▪ but Retreated back to their Trenches, after having lost near Five hundred and Sixty Men upon the place.</p>
            <p>This business of the Ravaline had so frighted our Citizens, that some of them began to murmur, and to say, That <hi>Staremberg would sacrifice them all to the fury of the Turks; that it was full time to make some agreement with the Enemy; that if he deferred it too long, they should have no Quarter given them; that it was the Emperors interest
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:199106:52"/> in this juncture of Affairs (since better could not be hoped for) to consider the Garison of</hi> Vienna <hi>as able to do good service to the Empire, and save it from the Turkish fury, provided the composition were in time.</hi> These dangerous di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scourses coming to the knowledge of <hi>Staremberg,</hi> he was once in a mind to punish exemplaryly such as could be known to have spoken so undescreetly, or rather Seditiously: But upon se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thoughts he resolved on another expedient, which was to publish an Order to this effect, That if any Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen or Officer in the Garison, of what rank or quality soever he was, should talk of surrendring the City, or making any sort of Composition, how seemingly advantagious soever, with the <hi>Turks,</hi> he should instantly be declared a Rebel, and punished ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. Which did so influence the Citizens, that whatever their thoughts were, they kept their Tongues within bounds; and being incouraged by the good hopes <hi>Staremberg</hi> gave them of relief, they appeared not to be much affriad of being Stormed by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:199106:52"/> the <hi>Turks,</hi> who, the Night following after their descent into the Ditch▪ had made a great Lodgement there, which they might do with the less difficulty, for that the deepness of the Ditch did secure them against the Great and Small Shot of the Besieged. Besides that, the Works they had raised were of a prodigious hight, and like Hills round the Attack of the Counterscarp, which did in a manner cover their passage into the Ditch.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Staremberg</hi> seeing he could not easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make attempts on the Enemy in this posture guarded, Commanded the Cannon to be pointed against these Works that covered the Enemies ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach. Twenty of the best Cannon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iers were called, and ordered to do their best endeavours to demolish these Mounts and Hills that did so much prejudice the City, and proved so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely advantageous to the Enemy. Our Cannon began to play at the break of day with such a fury, that before Two a Clock in the Afternoon the Hills were visibly lessened: About which time near a Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>intal of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:199106:53"/> Powder took Fire, and destroyed several Carriages and Cannoniers, and amongst others an <hi>Italian</hi> Renegado, much esteemed by the <hi>Turks</hi> for his great skill in the Art of Gunnery. The Thunder of the Cannon was continued with a like success till Night, at which time the Hills appeared to be near leveled with the Ground; yet <hi>Staremberg</hi> thought it not time to At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack the Enemy till the next Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Then with Two thousand chosen Men, he attaqued them with all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable vigour. The manner was thus: They made their Sally out at Two different Gates, with a design to meet together towards that part where the <hi>Turks</hi> had made their great Lodge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Ditch; They met with great opposition on all sides; but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheless overthrew with the loss of some Soldiers and Officers, all that stood in their way: And the passage of the <hi>Turks</hi> into the Ditch was laid open by our Cannon, and they expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed both to our small and great Shot; yet after an hours Ingagement, the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialists
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:199106:53"/> were forced to Retreat, because they had not Pioneers enough to ruine the Enemies Works.</p>
            <p>At the Evening a Counsel of War was held, and a second Attack resolved upon; there went out about a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand chosen men, the whole Garison being in a ready posture upon the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions, along the Ramparts, and in the great Streets, and publick places of the City; our Cannon in the mean time diverting the Enemy on all sides. They were at first fiercely beat back, almost into the City, by the <hi>Turks,</hi> the narrowness of the Ground obliging them to break their Files, whereby they could not make a considerable Front; and besides, were Charged in the Flank by a considerable number of <hi>Janizaries</hi> lying close in Ambuscade; so that this enterprize was like to prove very unsuccessful, if <hi>Staremberg</hi> himself had not rallyed our men, and set them a second time on work. In which the Enemy pursuing us, inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the same narrow passages; which ours observing, and by experience taught to lay hold on every favourable
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:199106:54"/> occasion; they beat the <hi>Turks</hi> back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to their Redoubts and Retrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with a considerable Slaughter; and after having demolished some of their Works, Retreated again into the City in good Order, being followed, but to little purpose, and at a great distance, by a considerable number of <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Staremberg</hi> judging it best to beat the Iron whilst it was hot, resolved to a third Attack, without giving respite to the Enemy, or to his Soldiers, who were more than ever in a humour to Fight. It was a while doubted of whether they should Sally out again, before the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of the Day, or not; but after some small debate about this matter, it was thought more expedient to make this third Attack about midnight, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt One and Two a Clock in the morning. The whole Garison then, and the Citizens were Commanded to be in readiness, and the general Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers went that Night up and down giving all necessary Orders. It was ordered that the Companies that had been already in Action, should take
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:199106:54"/> some refreshment, and keep the Basti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whilst Eight hundred fresh men should Sally out, with more than Eight hundred Pioniers, to the end they might ruine the Enemies Works raised against the City.</p>
            <p>They began their March in silence, between Eleven and Twelve a Clock at Night; <hi>Staremberg</hi> remembring them now and then of their Duty as they passed, and promising large recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to such as should distinguish them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves most signally in the performance of their Duty. They appeared all to be of a very chearful countenance, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved either to dye or vanquish. They took leave of one another as they went by, and bid a last farewel to their friends, embracing and kissing such as came near them; which <hi>Staremberg</hi> expresly discountenanced, as a thing not before this instant practised in this Garison, and seeming an untimely sort of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness, which might take off too much of the edge of a Marshal Courage. There was a great number of Torches lighted at several Gates, designedly to amuse the Enemy, least they should
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:199106:55"/> know what way our men intended; but they were on a suddain freed of this doubt, by a showre of Small Shot, that came frome whence they least ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected it. This entertainment in an inftant put the whole <hi>Turkish</hi> Army in a motion. The resistance in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Attack was such, that our first Files were twice broken by their Small Shot; but in an instant Rallied, Firing again so opportunely, that the Enemies were, at their turn, put into confusion. Which being observed by our Officers, they gave them not time to Rally, but followed them close, and cut in pieces all those that stood their ground, which some Companies of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizaries</hi> did with all imaginable obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, till they were broken by the <hi>Flanks</hi> and totally routed. The mean while the Pioneers were not idle, they ruined all the Enemies Works, burned their Gabions, and the greatest part of their Gallery. But all was not as yet done, the Retreat was not very easie, a great party of <hi>Turkish</hi> Horse and Foot advanced withal diligence to stop our passage into the City; which undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly they had performed, if <hi>Staremberg,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:199106:55"/> who had still a watchful eye upon all contingencies, had not prevented their design, by Charging them unexpected<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with Fifteen hundred choice Foot, which forced them to Retreat, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to us a free passage into the City, to the great satisfaction of the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and Incouragement of the whole Garison.</p>
            <p>The Enemy resolving on a revenge, gave us a general assault the Twenty first of <hi>August</hi> in the morning, of which take this short and true account: Some <hi>Janizaries</hi> that were taken Prison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, inform'd Count <hi>Staremberg,</hi> that it was generally reported in the that the Grand Vizier had resolved to Attack the City in a more furious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner than he had done hitherto; and that for that purpose great preparations were making; so that he hoped either to force us by Storm, or compel us to surrender upon thoughts how little we were able to stand out after this general Assault. They further added, that the <hi>Turks,</hi> from the beginning of the Siege, had lost more than Twenty thousand of their best men; and that it would never have been undertaken, if the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:199106:56"/> Grand Vizier had thought to have met with so v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gorous a resistance. They said likewise, that he was informed the City was destitute of all necessary provisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, at least of many things requisite for a considerable or long defence; that the <hi>Turks</hi> were now beginning to mistrust their good fortune, and somewhat to dispond of a good success in this Siege; because that it began to be generally reported, that the King of <hi>Poland</hi> was upon his March at the head of a strong Army, accompanied by his Son; and that the Auxiliary Troops were coming a-pace to the King of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> (for so they called him) not knowing what distinction we put between a King and a Soveraign Prince. That nevertheless the Grand Vizier was resolv'd to lose his Life before <hi>Vienna</hi> rather than Raise the Siege; and that trusting to the Number and Courage of his Army, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting of the best Officers, and stoutest Soldiers of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, he would undoubtedly venture a Battel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the whole Christian Forces uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted together. Tho' all this was reflected on by <hi>Staremberg, Capeliers,</hi> and other Officers of the Garison, yet their main
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:199106:56"/> concern in the present juncture of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, was to inquire of the true time and manner of the formentioned As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sault; whereof they could give no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther account, save only, that if it suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded not, the <hi>Turks</hi> would be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly discourag'd, and would perhaps raise the Siege by the Grand Siegnicr's Command, who, they said, had not much approv'd of this enterprize, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining more to sweep all away before him, than to Attack the Imperial Seat, and leave behind the Island of <hi>Schutz, Raab, Gomorra</hi> and <hi>Presburg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prisoners dismissed, a Counsel of War was held; whereof, as likewise of what they were informed, a short ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count was sent to the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> by a Fisherman that Swam the River.</p>
            <p>The <hi>21st</hi> of <hi>August,</hi> all such as were able to carry Arms in the City were Commanded to draw to their Colours, in the usual places, whence, after they had been provided with Match, Powder, and other necessaries, they were ordered to retire to their respect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive stations till further Orders.</p>
            <p>About midnight a hot Alarm was given us by the Enemies, who sprang
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:199106:57"/> two Mines not far from one another under the <hi>Lebel Bastion;</hi> but had little or no effect, because they were disap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by our Countermines. Another Mine they were about to Spring, but were not time enough, because they were prevented by some of our Subter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean Works, who seising upon their Miners under ground, brought them forth Prisoners, and took away the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which was already laid together with the Match not as yet kindled. This petty success gave us some hopes of a greater, which happened in the following manner: We observed a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral motion in every part of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Camp, which some looked upon as a disposition to Retreat, but in reallity was nothing else, but the Marching of several Detachments, making up toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a considerable Body, in order to give the lately mentioned general As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sault; which was preceeded both by their great and small Shot, whereever they could discover us. We answered them with the same Musick, but with a far greater loss on their side than ours, as having the advantage of the scitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and both Cannoniers and Marks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:199106:57"/> nothing inferior, if not better than theirs. This sport, which was but a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble to some greater attempt, lasted above two hours: But then on a sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain the Enemy Marched on all sides towards the Ditch, so thick, and in such a crowd, that we had some reason to fear our being overpowered by the number: But we fired our Cannon from the Wings of the Bastions, and other parts so often, that we put them now and then to a stand, till they had either withdrawn, or marched over the huge heaps of the dead. In the mean while our Forces in the Out-works were not idle, and resisted the Enemy every where, without yielding one foot of ground, except in some parts where the number was two unequal. But <hi>Starem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> with the rest of the Garison Sallied out, and gave the Enemy on all sides a general overthrow; who, notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their great loss, and our obstinate resistance, had already beaten down with their great Cannon, the <hi>Scots-gate,</hi> and rendred themselves Masters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, with their Swords in their Hands; which put the whole City for a while in a great consternation: But <hi>Starem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg's</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:199106:58"/> undaunted Courage, and chearful Countinance, inspir'd the whole Garison with a new vigour. He Retreated back on a suddain to the City, and although wounded in the Shoulder with an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, took no rest, till he had repossested himself of the <hi>Scots-gate,</hi> which he did before the <hi>Turks</hi> had made any consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Lodgement. He Attacked them with such a fury, but withal, such Order, that notwithstanding their vigorous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance, they were all cut off in less than half an hour. Which Action ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded to by the Shouts of the Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, Beating of Drums, Timbals, and Sounding of Trumpets, was followed by a general Retreat of the <hi>Turkish</hi> Forces, without having got other ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage in this hot dispute, than making an inconsiderable Lodgement at the foot of a Bastion, whence the next day, by an unexpected Sally out from the City, they were dislodg'd. The loss of the <hi>Turks</hi> in this Attack was little less than Six or Seven thousand Men; on our side we had near Fifteen hundred killed or unserviceable; amongst whom were several considerable Officers slain on the place.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:199106:58"/>
            <p>This Action discouraged infinitely the Grand <hi>Vizier,</hi> who was inraged at the great loss, and did begin to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage his Men with more discretion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst a better occasion. He was three or four days, though not idle, yet not very busie, his Trenches not going on with the wonted diligence.</p>
            <p>About this time we got News which was publickly Read in the hearing of a part of the Garison, to the great rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing thereof; and so much the more surprizing, in regard so little expected. It was told us then, that the Grand <hi>Vizier</hi> having sent off a Body of 15000 <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> to surprise the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> marching in order to his joyning with the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> that this Duke had faced about, and given them Battel with so good success, that they were intirely overthrown, few of them escaping Death either by the Sword or the Water. This Victory in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spired us all with a new vigour, and put us in great hopes of a greater Victory. In the mean time we were still hand to hand contending with the Enemy, who did continue to molest us with sudden
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:199106:59"/> small Attacks; which I so term, as no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> considerable in comparison of that I have already spoken of.</p>
            <p>This City was about this time gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally afflicted by an Epidemical distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, a <hi>Dyssentery,</hi> or Bloody Flux, which carried off sometimes Threescore or more in one day. The Governour himself was not free of it, though he never kept within doors: and when he was so weak that he could not walk or ride, he caus'd himself to be carried whither 'twas requisite for him to be. The Rumour was a while in the <hi>Turkish</hi> Army, that he was dead; which caus'd such an universal Joy amongst the <hi>Turks,</hi> that they made upon this account Bonfires, hoping that now the City would be soon yielded up. But their Joy was but short; for they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd d the day following, by a person they had taken Prisoner from our Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, of the contrary, and that he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd to defend the same to the utmost, and had as yet a Garison strong enough to resist several Weeks, or at least till the arrival of the Christian Forces for the relief of the City.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:199106:59"/>
            <p>We were informed on the other side by fome <hi>Janizaries</hi> taken Prisoners, that the <hi>Turkish</hi> Army was beginning to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer much for want of necessary Provisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which were sold at very high rates in their Camp; that their greatest want was that of Forrage, the adjacent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try being quite desolated; that the dead Horses did infect their whole Army; that the Bloody Flux had already al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most ruin'd, or at least much weaken'd some quarters of the Army; that the daily loss, what by the Sword, and what by various Distempers, was estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to amount to more than a thousand Men; that the Grand <hi>Vizier</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd between the <hi>29th</hi> of <hi>August,</hi> and the <hi>2d</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> to give so many and so furious Assaults to <hi>Vienna,</hi> that he doubted not but that he should take it by Storm before the arrival of the Auxiliary-Troops, and the junction of all the Christian Forces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Staremberg</hi> after he had given an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count hereof, and of the Condition of the City, to the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered all the Citizens, and part of the Garison, to lend their helping hands to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:199106:60"/> the retrenchments he was a making be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the <hi>Scots</hi> Gate, the <hi>Lebel</hi> Bastion, and other the most important pieces of Fortification; resolving to dispute e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very foot of ground with the Enemy, from whom he expected no Quarter. And in case he had been overpower'd by their Number, all was in a readiness for the blowing up of the Bastions, that nothing might remain after such a long Siege, but an open Village; and then to cut his way thorow the midst of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, with the remainder of his Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</p>
            <p>The <hi>29th</hi> we perceived the <hi>Turkish</hi> Forces drawing up in Battalia round the City, and detachments going off every moment towards the Ditch. Whence we concluded they were resolv'd to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der themselves Masters thereof. A thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand of our men were lodg'd in the Ditch, who got instantly a supply of seven hundred more, which was all we could well spare; but with this order, that after a vigorous resistance, they should retreat into the City, and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the Ditch to the Enemy, when they could no longer defend the same,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:199106:60"/> their number being so much impair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>About ten a clock in the morning, the <hi>Turks</hi> came fiercely on with their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary shoots and <hi>halloo's,</hi> but were put a while to a stand, and somewhat in confusion, by our great and small shot. They went on notwithstanding their great loss, and were received vigorously by that part of our Garison that was to engate them: But our men according to their Orders by little and little gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ground, retreated orderly into the City, where they were instantly divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and sent to the Bastions and Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part; for them onely now we had to defend, the Enemy being Master of all our Out-works. Yet <hi>Staremberg</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving observ'd, that the lodgments the <hi>Turks</hi> had made in the Ditch were but slight, and not well Guarded, sallied out with a part of his Garison, and cleared the Ditch of them on one part of the City. After his retreat, he was infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by an <hi>Italian</hi> Renagado, who had sled to us from the <hi>Turks,</hi> that there was a Mine ready to be sprung under the <hi>Lebel</hi> Bastion; whereupon he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:199106:61"/> three Companies, that were upon Duty there, to retire; and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly after their retreat, the Mine over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned the whole Face and Left-Wing of the Bastion into the Ditch: which good success incourag'd the Enemies to try if they could make a Lodgment up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. But they were twice repulsed with great loss, occasioned by our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual firing from behind our retrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Yet at length they prevailed, and made a considerable Lodgment in the mid'st of the Bastion.</p>
            <p>We were never in a greater Distress than in this Conjuncture, and began to look upon our selves as lost men; though fully resolved to spend the last drop of our Blood, rather than surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Staremberg</hi> thinking it not secure to give the Enemies leisure to Fortify themselves upon this Bastion, upon which they had already some great pieces of Ordnance mounted, ready to play upon the City, and those places e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially where we were accustomed to draw up our men in; commanded 1800 chosen Souldiers to attack the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:199106:61"/>
               <hi>Turks</hi> with their Swords in their hands, followed by a hundred Pioniers, to ruine immediately, if the enterprise suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, their Lodgment. They entred the Gorge (or Neck) of the Bastion, notwithstanding the Enemies resistance; and after a rude Combat of about a quarter of an hour, they beat them off with the slaughter of about two hundred Janizaries, and a <hi>Bassa</hi> that commanded them.</p>
            <p>Our men kept their ground, and did whatever cou'd be expected from experienced Souldiers, having clear'd more than once with their small Shot that part of the Ditch they could dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover from the left Wing of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion; and covering themselves in the breach, made a new retrenchment; which so discourag'd the <hi>Turks,</hi> that they never attempted again the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest of the Bastion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> well knowing that we were in a readiness to oppose them whenever they should appear on the breach.</p>
            <p>Their Attacks were not now so open as before, but more dangerous, because under ground, and hidden; they were
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:199106:62"/> busie Mining every where: And on our side likewise, we were not idle, but doing our utmost endeavours, either to find their Mines, or give them Air by our Countermines. Wherein we had often greater success than we expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, or the Enemies designed.</p>
            <p>They had already undermined not onely the Bastion of the Court, but were heard working under the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Palace: which so affrighted our Enginiers, that surpised to hear the Enemies beneath them, they retreated instantly out of the Mines, for fear of being blown up. Herein <hi>Staremberg</hi> was forced to make use partly of his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, partly fair words and large promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, to ingage them to do what lay in their power to discover the Enemies Mines. Thus incourag'd, they set to work again, and taking deeper measures than they had done at first, met happily with the <hi>Turkish</hi> Miners, killed some of 'em, and brought the rest up Prisoners, taking out of their Mines several Quintals (or hundreds) of Powder. This was a most signal service; and I may confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently say, the happy discovery of this
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:199106:62"/> Mine, saved this City from being taken by the <hi>Turks,</hi> who were expecting the event thereof; and so to fall in upon us on all sides, resolv'd, as it was credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly reported, to have made a general onset with their whole Infantry: and undoubtedly they had succeeded; for we were beginning to want all necessary's. Our Grenades, which do great executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on such occasions, were all spent; our Garison was much diminish'd, consisting now but of six thousand Men; the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals were become scarce, and the Bloody-Flux was become almost Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal. But the news of the Arrival and junction of the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> the Auxiliary Troops, and the Imperial Army at <hi>Crembs,</hi> inspir'd us all with a new Life and Vigour, and we doubted not now any more of defending our selves at least till such time as the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians Army came to our relief, unless some unexpected accident should hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen; which we had always reason to be somewhat affraid of, because of the Enemies great skill in Mining.</p>
            <p>The 3d 4th and 8th of <hi>September</hi> they Attack't us again most desperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:199106:63"/> but both to their great loss, and ours. They had once <hi>Arbored</hi> the <hi>Crescent</hi> upon the Bastions against the Grand <hi>Viziers</hi> Quarters, and had in all likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood put us all to the Sword, if <hi>Starem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> who was always in Action, had not run thither, followed by conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Detachments</hi> of all our Forces. The Enemies were scarce able to abide his first Charge, but were at the second in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely routed, and most of 'em put to the Sword, or thrown down headlong into the Ditch.</p>
            <p>This Victory weakned very much our Garison, so that <hi>Staremberg</hi> judg'd it now full time to give the Signs agreed upon betwixt him and the Duke of <hi>Lorain,</hi> of his being reduced to the last extremity. Which accordingly was done, after this manner: The <hi>11th</hi> of <hi>September</hi> between eleven and twelve at night, with a strong Guard he went round the City, and gave his Orders e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where, with a special. Command to the Cannoniers to make all the Noise they could with their Cannon, Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets in the mean time Sounding, the Drums and Timbalds beating. But
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:199106:63"/> that the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> might better know what he meant, he caused all Night-<hi>Fusees,</hi> and divers sorts of Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works, to be cast up into the Air, which was the main sign of his utmost distress agreed upon between him and the Duke of <hi>Lorrain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Enemy was somewhat perplex'd at our extraordinary mirth, but could not well judge what could be the real occasion thereof, save onely that they could not but know that we were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting every moment the arrival of the Christian Army, consisting of near 80000 Horse and Foot: neither was our expectation in vain; for General <hi>Dunwalt</hi> had already possessed himself of an important passage in the Forest of <hi>Vienna,</hi> to facilitate the March of the Christians Army towards the <hi>Turkish</hi> Camp.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Poland,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lorain,</hi> and the whole Christian Forces, came within sight of the <hi>Turks</hi> the <hi>12th</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> about nine a Clock in the Morning. Our Governour instantly commanded all such as were capable of service to be in a readiness. The Grand
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:199106:64"/>
               <hi>Vizier</hi> seem'd resolved to stand his ground, and send out a great Body of men to observe the Countenance of the Christian Army; whose advanc'd ground was Attack'd, and put to flight by Colonel <hi>Heusler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Christian Army marching close, advanc'd in good order towards the <hi>Turkish</hi> Camp: The King of <hi>Poland</hi> was at the head of his own Army, and upon level ground against the Grand <hi>Viziers</hi> Quarters, upon which he fell heavily. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and the other <hi>German</hi> Gentlemen, omitted that day no part of their Duty; having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved themselves with all imaginable Conduct and Valour. After a Vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous but short resistance, the Christians enter'd on all sides the <hi>Turkish</hi> Camp, where they found the Spahi's and Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries drawn up in several Bodies.</p>
            <p>The Grand <hi>Vizier</hi> in this dangerous position of Affairs, took a sudden and Generous resolution, which, if success<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, had proved fatal to us first, and then to the Christian Army. He caused two Mines to be sprung under the Ramparts of the City, not far from
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:199106:64"/> the <hi>Scots Gate,</hi> which made a breach large enough for thirtie men to march in a front; though not without incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, because the ground was not much levelled, though overturn'd. <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remberg</hi> caused without delay ten great Guns to be set upon the breach, loaden with Musquet - balls, broken Horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoo's, and such-like things. We won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd at first at this attempt of the <hi>Turks,</hi> in presence of the Christian Army; and whilst they were very uncertain of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory. But the Grand <hi>Vizier</hi>'s design was, in case he should take the City by Storm, which he doubted not but he could, having the advantage of such a great breach, to draw instantly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Walls of the City, and under the Cannon thereof, his Baggage, Cannon, Tents, and the whole Train of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, that so it should be his Choice to venture or not venture a Battel as he thought fittest.</p>
            <p>Our Governour was extreamly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd at this unexpected accident; for he was preparing for a general sallie out against those that kept the Trenches, and had lodg'd themselves every where
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:199106:65"/> in the Ditch; but was now forc'd to expose his best men against an infinite number of <hi>Turks,</hi> crowding in at the breach with all imaginable bravery. The ground was disputed on each side for half an hour, with an inconceivable obstinacy, both parties being equally incouraged by certain hopes of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory. But at length the <hi>Turks</hi> were prevail'd upon, and repulsed with a great loss of their best men. They were once more returning to the breach, but the Cannon which had done us still good service, laid their fury, and broke them quite; so that they retreated back again to their Trenches, there to expect new orders from the Grand <hi>Vizier,</hi> and the event of the general Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel. In the mean time, <hi>Staremberg</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that the <hi>Turks</hi> began to yield their ground to the Christians, sallied out, as he had first resolv'd, against those that were left to keep the Trenches, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially over against the wide breach, that had given occasion to this great and last Attack. After a vigorous resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, he cut in pieces more than Four thousand <hi>Janizaries,</hi> whilst on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:199106:65"/> side, the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> Prince <hi>Waldeck,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>German</hi> Princes, were putting to flight and to the Sword the <hi>Turkish</hi> Horse and Infantry; which being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of by our Citizens and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, they could scarce be holden with in the Gates from pursuing the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
            <p>The whole Christian Army now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near forty eight hours in Action, from the beginning of its March, could not pursue the Enemy, but stood in battel-array all that night, and express Order being issued out from the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, That no man under pain of Death should quit his Rank to Plunder, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an express Command from the High Officers, lest the Enemy, as has often happened, should sallie on a sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and get an easie Victory over an Army put into disorder by the libertic of Plundering, which was onely granted to the Christian Troops the next day at twelve a clock.</p>
            <p>The Booty that private Souldiers and several Officers made, of all things
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:199106:66"/> that either men have need of in long Journies, or Armies in great enterprizes, was of an inesteemable Value: The Quintals of Powder, Lead, Oyls, Match, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were in a greater number than had ever been seen in any <hi>Turkish</hi> Army: They left behind them Four hundred pieces Cannon small and great, Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets and Granado's more than Forty thousand, Thirty thousand Tents or more; with all other Necessaries belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to a great Army.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turkish</hi> Enginiers being under ground, knew nothing as yet of the raising of the Siege; and having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated some new Mines, came to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint, as they were wont, the Grand <hi>Vizier</hi> with what they had done, and receive his Orders, as to the fittest time of springing their Mines: they were at first overjoy'd, thinking the <hi>Turks,</hi> whom they saw no more, had possessed themselves of the City: but being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly made sensible of their Mistake, they beg'd on their knees quarter from the <hi>Germans,</hi> who told them they must first discover their Mines, and carry out the Powder they had put in them, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:199106:66"/> then they should know their Doom; which done, they were put to the Sword: But before they died, exact in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry was made concerning the Chief Enginiers of the <hi>Turkish</hi> Army; they answered that they were the men, and the chief Masters in the Art of Mining among the <hi>Turks;</hi> which some hearing, they were of opinion they should have their lives, being men of Parts, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to render good Service to the Emperour. But 'tis too well known, that the <hi>Turks</hi> seldom prove sincere Converts to the Christian Religion; and such men would undoubtedly leave us, if they were spared, to the great damage of the Christians, to whom they might prove exceedingly prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial on the like occasion. This Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on prevailing, they were instantly cut off, to the number of Twenty three, whereof Five were Renegado's, and the rest Native <hi>Turks.</hi> Greater severity hapned to the sick the Enemy had left in the Camp, who were about Three thousand, for the most part afflicted with a Bloody Flux, contracted by their ill Dyet, more especially by eating of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:199106:67"/> Horse-flesh, which being of a very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>common digestion, caused an ill habit, which immediately turn'd to a White Flux with Gripes, and soon after dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated into a Dyssenterie, or Bloody Flux. Of these miserable Wretches the Souldiers, without expecting any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther order from <hi>Staremberg,</hi> were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to make a Sacrifice to the Flame, and for the purification of the Air (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying them the Honour of Dying by their Swords) which on them all they most cruelly performed; though not without decrying, and for which some of the Ringleaders were punished. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, by an express order of the chief Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, the Prisoners were commanded to bury the Dead, to cast them into the River, to fill up the Trenches, and level the works raised by the <hi>Turks, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Imperial Majesty, the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and all the Christian Generals entered the City, which they found exceedingly defaced by the Enemies Bombs and Cannon. The Emperour shewed all imaginable Kindness to <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remberg,</hi> and spoke of him in most ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable terms, acknowledged that the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:199106:67"/> whole Empire, and all Christendom were infinitely oblig'd to his good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and Valour; that he could expect nothing less in time and place, than an adequate reward. The King of <hi>Poland</hi> embrac'd him, and kept him close to his breast for a considerable time, with sutable expressions of his esteem, and love for his person. The Duke of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain,</hi> and the other Princes of the Empire, spoke no less kindly to him, with parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Elogiums of his Prudent and Vigorous defence and management.</p>
            <p>Thus the second Siege of <hi>Vienna</hi> by the <hi>Turks</hi> was raised, to the immortal Glory of that City, and the eternal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown of those that contributed most to its delivery. The King of <hi>Poland</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be praised enough for his Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Courage: his Name is become now more terrible to the Infidels, than ever was that of <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> or <hi>Huniades.</hi> The Empire shall be eternally oblig'd to him, for venturing himself, his Son and his Crown for its relief: this is an Example of a true Christian Generosity, which may be admir'd, perhaps envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but a doubt whether ever imitated.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:199106:68"/> We shall have all the reason in the World to think well of Providence, or Divine goodness, were it pleased to spare this great man, that may prove the Scourge and Ruine of the <hi>Turkish</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</p>
            <p>Neither can the Duke of <hi>Lorrain's</hi> good Conduct be enough commended, whereof he has not onely given good proof in the taking of <hi>Philipsburg,</hi> in presence of an Army of 40000 men Commanded by the Duke of <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg;</hi> but in this juncture of Affairs, wherein he has surpassed even Envy it self: this great man was at first com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Emperour to Attack <hi>Newhawsel,</hi> and after a good progress made; order'd to withdraw; which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate beginning of the Campaigne, could not but prove a great discourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both to himself and his Army; Yet such was his Address, that at the approach of the Grand <hi>Vizier</hi> with 150000 fighting men, his Army being but a hand full in comparison of the <hi>Turks,</hi> he retreated with the loss but of some of his Baggage, and about five or eight hundred Dragoons; saving his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantry
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:199106:68"/> in the Island of <hi>Schutz,</hi> and bringing off his Cavaldry for securing <hi>Vienna,</hi> which the <hi>Turks</hi> thought to have surprized, but were prevented by his fortunate diligence in sending <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remburg</hi> and <hi>Caplieres</hi> with 12000 Foot, and 1500 Dragoons, in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nick of time that the <hi>Tartars</hi> arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on the other side of the City near <hi>Leopolstadt;</hi> and retiring afterwards to <hi>Crembs</hi> with a little Body of about 18000 Horse and Foot, waited for the Auxiliary Troops of the Empire, letting pass no occasion of serving the besieged. He had his Spies that went to and fro, into the <hi>Turkish</hi> Camp, and into the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with Letters to <hi>Staremberg.</hi> He beat the <hi>Turks</hi> in all Rancounters, and being inform'd that Count <hi>Teckely</hi> was marching with an Army towards <hi>Presbarg,</hi> upon the account of some secret intelligence he there managed; March'd on a sudden, leaving behind him the <hi>Turkish</hi> Camp, presented Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel to the Enemie; but not being accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he fell upon the Rear so heavily, that he put the whole Army in disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and forced the Enemy to abandon
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:199106:69"/> his Cannon and Baggage, besides the loss of his Boat-Bridge, which was burned, and more than 800 men slain on the place. He retreated to <hi>Crembs</hi> again, after having Fortified that Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son with some hundreds of men, and so secured that City to the Emperour. The <hi>Turks</hi> so much fear'd his good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, that they durst not Attack him in his Camp, but onely when he was marching in order to his joyning with the King of <hi>Poland;</hi> but this cost dear, as I elsewhere related, being shamefully beat.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> the Prince <hi>Waldeck,</hi> and all the other <hi>German</hi> Princes, shall have their deserved places in the History of our times, with due Elogiums of their good Conduct, Valour, and Zeal for the common good of Christendom. The Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> likewise, (for why should not the Devil have his due if he deserve it?) is highly to be commended for his effectual Zeal in this conjuncture towards the promoting of the Christian Interest, by the great and constant sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of Money sent to the Fmperour,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:199106:69"/> the onely thing he most stood in need of; <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Poland</hi> surnishing him with men enough. The King of <hi>Spain</hi> open'd likewise his Treasures, and gave the Emperour considerable summes of Money. As to the <hi>French</hi> King, let some Male-contents or other say what they please; the service he hath done the Empire (not to judge of intentions) in not Attacking it, as he might have done with great advantage whilest the <hi>Germans</hi> were ingaged on the other side against the <hi>Turks,</hi> may bespeak him either generous, or so little careful of his own interest, that he has let slip the best occasion that he shall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver perhaps have hereafter, of possessing himself of <hi>Philipsburg, Spire, Mayence, Treve,</hi> &amp;c. though perhaps some may think as I do, that such a War in this conjuncture had not been consistent with the Honour of a Most Christian King, how much soever to his advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
            <p>His Majesty of Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> though less concerned, wanted neither Zeal nor good will to lend a helping hand to the <hi>Germans,</hi> against the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:199106:70"/> Enemy of Christendom: but his Domestick Affairs, or rather Broyls, which we hope are over, by Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>special Providence over these three Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and his Majesties Princely Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Wise conduct, gave some im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment.</p>
            <p>But for the Readers intire satisfaction, let us take another view of the present State of <hi>Europe,</hi> with some peculiar re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and due regard to the true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of the most considerable Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Princes, in relation to the <hi>German</hi> Affairs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Europe,</hi> the most Warlike part of the known World, is overpower'd, or at least in some manner awed by two most Potent Princes, the Emperour of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire on the one side, and the <hi>French</hi> King on the other. The Grand <hi>Signior</hi> aims at the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest of <hi>Germany,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> begin to hope (of late) they shall outdo him, already looking upon the greatest part of <hi>Europe</hi> as belonging to them, <hi>Par un droit de bienseance,</hi> As a piece of ground that is not able to defend it self, and they may when they please be Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:199106:70"/> thereof. These two Princes have such an influence upon the rest of <hi>Europe,</hi> that whensoever they are in Movement the other <hi>European</hi> Princes cannot repose; but must of force resolve to stir, for their own preservation. Yet <hi>Germany</hi> by this late Victory, is now in such a posture, that in all likelihood the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> will chase the <hi>Turks</hi> out of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary.</hi> A Conquest that will secure the Hereditary Provinces from another <hi>Turkish</hi> Invasion: although a greater progress may be expected, because of the Union of the Protestant and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Princes, which will render <hi>Germany</hi> Invincible, and terrible to all it's Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, especially to the <hi>French,</hi> for whose welfare no <hi>German</hi> Prince whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Protestant or Romanist hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much Zeal. The Marquess of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> 'tis true is somewhat ingag'd in the <hi>French</hi> interest, but nevertheless sticks close to the common Cause of the Empire: And though he sent not his Forces he had in readiness to the relief of <hi>Vienna,</hi> upon the account of some other private ingagements, yet he sent the King of <hi>Poland</hi> a considerable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:199106:71"/> of men, in execution of an ancient Treaty between him and that Crown. We must never the less confess, that <hi>Germany</hi> is still threatn'd, and hath all reason to be afraid both of the <hi>Turks</hi> and the <hi>French.</hi> The <hi>Turks,</hi> though overcome before <hi>Vienna,</hi> are not as yet chased out of <hi>Hungary;</hi> and who knows how soon the present Condition of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs may change? On the other side, the <hi>Germans</hi> may look back upon the <hi>French</hi> King, as a more terrible Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, in case they fear his Yoke, as some of them perhaps do more than that of the Gand <hi>Seignor,</hi> how heavy soever. Now since this mightie Prince is pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed of <hi>Strasburg,</hi> one of the Richest, Greatest, and Strongest Cities in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> he has all imaginable incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to undertake upon the Liberty of that Nation, having such a considerable advantage for repossessing himself of <hi>Philipsburg,</hi> that in all likelihood it will be lost to the Empire if he attack it. For what hindred most his progress in <hi>Germany</hi> in the late Wars, was the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a free passage upon the <hi>Rhine</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the lower part of <hi>Alsatia.</hi> But
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:199106:71"/> now having the Bridge of <hi>Strasburg</hi> under the command of an impregnable Fort, he is the absolute Master of that River, upon which he may convey easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly towards <hi>Philipsburg</hi> all necessaries for a besieging Army. The main inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest then, and chief concern of the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Princes, I mean as to their Strength in general, consists in their Union toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; without which, the greatest King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the World are suddenly torn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sunder and destroyed. Yet must it be confessed in particular, that those <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Princes who are upon the <hi>French</hi> Frontiers, are somewhat drawn by their own Interest to comply rather with the <hi>French</hi> than with the Empire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are in danger to be ruined or conquered by them, ere the Emperour and Empire can be in a readiness to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them. But to this difficulty the answer is at hand, and obvious: for such petty Princes must defend themselves, not by their own <hi>puissance,</hi> which is not to be compared to that of <hi>France,</hi> but by their inseparable adherency to the body of the Empire, which will endure many a shock before it fall: They are
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:199106:72"/> not to undertake alone a War against such a potent Prince as the <hi>French</hi> King; For such a rashness cannot but prove their total ruine. But thus provided, if they be attack'd by him, they need not much to fear, the whole body of the <hi>German</hi> Commonwealth being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concern'd in their case, as subsisting on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the safety of its Members, and more especially of such as have their Station near the Confines of a great Prince. Gold ('tis confest) which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can resist, may slip perhaps the Knot, or at least hinder the good effects of the strongest Confederacy: But then our Supposition would be chang'd, and Division occupy the place of Union, which we say is so necessary for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of <hi>Germany,</hi> that whatever way it be dissolved, whether by fear, or by fair and large promises, or present advantages, its Enemies will undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prevail to its utter ruine and destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>It's no less now the concern of the <hi>Cantons</hi> of <hi>Switzerland</hi> to agree among themselves; for they are, I may say, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready under the <hi>French</hi> Yoke, since
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:199106:72"/> the Conquest of the <hi>Franch County</hi> made by <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great. <hi>Brisac, Friburg</hi> in <hi>Brisgo,</hi> and the Fortress <hi>Huningen</hi> upon the <hi>Rhine</hi> a little below <hi>Basil,</hi> put that City almost in the power of the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I shall say little of the <hi>Swedes,</hi> who begin now to open their eyes, and are convinced, that it is not secure for them to attack <hi>Germany,</hi> there being now no Faction in the Empire, as formerly in <hi>Gustavus</hi> his time, to call them in to their helpe. And they are too far separated from the <hi>French,</hi> to receive from them necessary Supplies, if they were attack'd at the same time by the <hi>Germans</hi> and <hi>Danes,</hi> as indeed they were in the late Wars, to their great disadvantage: their only standing is by the House of <hi>Austria</hi> &amp; the Empire, in this juncture of Affairs, the K. of <hi>Denmark</hi> being now powerfully assisted by the <hi>French;</hi> besides, the late Alliance of the Prince of <hi>Denmark</hi> with the Princess of <hi>England,</hi> may perhaps give the <hi>Swedes</hi> occasion to fear lest <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> should favour the <hi>Danes</hi> to their prejudice. So as things are now, they must of necessity have recourse to the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:199106:73"/> Empire, and the House of <hi>Austria,</hi> for their own security.</p>
            <p>The Commonwealth of <hi>Genoa</hi> upon a not unlike account is ingaged in the <hi>Spanish</hi> Interest: it is threatned by the <hi>French,</hi> who having now <hi>Casal</hi> in their power, are in a condition to undertake all in <hi>Italy;</hi> and <hi>Genoa</hi> being one of the richest and best Cities of that Kingdom, it may allure some day the <hi>French</hi> to pay a Visit in a not ordinary pomp to the <hi>Genoeses;</hi> which they understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and fearing it may happen but too soon, have drawn up with the <hi>Spaniards</hi> their strongest Neighbours, though now (such is the unconstancy of humane Things) become so weak, that they are not able to defend themselves; and for that reason they have recourse to the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> ingag'd by a principle of self-preservation to lend them a helping hand: But both in all appearance must hereafter depend upon <hi>England,</hi> if they will avoid their utter Ruine.</p>
            <p>On this occasion, for the satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Curious, I shall state here these three Questions, to be resolved af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Problematical method, without deciding any thing my self.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:199106:73"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The First,</hi> Whether <hi>England</hi> be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the conservation of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Low Countries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second,</hi> Whether the Conquest of <hi>Holland</hi> by the <hi>French,</hi> would be of a dangerous consequence for <hi>England,</hi> as 'tis commonly believed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Third,</hi> Whether the Conquest of <hi>Holland</hi> would prove a real Advantage to the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the first, it seems that <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> as 'tis generally talk'd all <hi>Europe</hi> over, is extreamly concern'd in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of that part of the Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries which belongs as yet to the Crown of <hi>Spain;</hi> because it is a Maxime of State, observed from all times, and by all wise Princes, to put a stop to the too excessive growing Greatness of their Neighbours. This was exactly practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth; who seeing that <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth was come to an extraordinary pitch of Grandeur, by the overthrow of the <hi>French</hi> King in <hi>Italy,</hi> broke from him, and joyn'd with the <hi>French,</hi> not upon the account of any particular Kindness he had for that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but with intent onely to even the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:199106:74"/> ballance again, and stop the current of the Emperours victorious Arms, who aspired to no less in those daies, than to to the Dignitie of an Universal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch. And it may be presumed at this time, that the <hi>French</hi> King is no less terrible to <hi>Europe,</hi> if not more, than <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth was then. His vast Treasures, his Arbitrary and Absolute Power, his great Conquests in <hi>Italy, Flanders</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> the number of his strong Cities, of his experienced Officers, and <hi>Veteran</hi> Souldiers, besides the advantageous scituation of his Kingdom, in the very Center of <hi>Europe;</hi> all this, I say, laid together, cannot but make us look upon him as a most migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Prince, whose growing Grandeur will in all likelihood prove fatal to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and may at length prove de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive to his other Neighbours, if they prevent not in time their own destruction. 'Tis evident then, as it is most generally discoursed, that through a principle of Self-preservation, we are concern'd to hinder, if we can, the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Netherlands</hi> from being Conquered by the <hi>French,</hi> who by this addition to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:199106:74"/> their Empire, will be in an advantageous posture to possess themselves of <hi>Holland,</hi> a necessary step to their Universal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy. The <hi>Germans</hi> understood the Consequence of this Conquest, when the <hi>French</hi> were very near it in the late Wars against <hi>Holland,</hi> and unanimously joyn'd their Forces in order to save, not so much the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> as themselves, from being subdued by the <hi>French.</hi> Whence it appears, that our Concern is the same in this case, and rather the more, because the <hi>French</hi> King by this Conquest, seems to gain ground upon us, and still draw nearer and nearer to our Coasts, which he may at length be enabled to invade, to the endangering of our Properties and Liberties, and the Honour of this Nation.</p>
            <p>This is the Opinion of most men, and the general resolution of the Question above stated; though some others, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly sagacious, and of a profound Judgment, considering things under a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Bias, will have us to judge other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise. They grant the Conquest of the <hi>Spanish Netherlands</hi> will prove a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Addition to the <hi>French</hi> Empire,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:199106:75"/> and render that Nation more terrible both to the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Hollanders;</hi> which they say will be of an infinite advantage to <hi>England.</hi> For both <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> in this case will be forced, as being press'd by the <hi>French,</hi> to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from Sea their greatest strength within themselves, and so we shall be the sole Masters of all the Trade of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> which cannot but redound to the great benefit of great <hi>Britain.</hi> The <hi>Spaniards</hi> in this conjuncture will be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blig'd to make advantageous offers to <hi>England,</hi> as not being able to stand their own ground, without our help. By which means we might be possest of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stend,</hi> or some other important <hi>Spanish</hi> Harbour on the other side, the onely thing <hi>England</hi> wants to render it consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable abroad. To this they add, that though the <hi>French</hi> were Masters of the <hi>Spanish Netherlands,</hi> 'tis no sure conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence that they should conquer <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> For besides that their Country is strongly defended by its natural scitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the States-General have conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Forces on foot, Commanded by a Prince of great Courage, and good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:199106:75"/> though not hitherto so fortunate as he deserves. Their Frontier Towns are well fortified, and their Treasures great enough to raise great Armies: They have moreover a considerable number of experienced Officers of their own Nation, and many Forreigners, as <hi>English, Scots, Germans,</hi> and <hi>Irish.</hi> And as to their power at Sea, 'tis greater yet than that of the <hi>French;</hi> and undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly with a strong Fleet they would make a great diversion towards the <hi>French</hi> Coast. We must not then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, because of the easie Conquest of <hi>Holland</hi> in Seventy two, that the <hi>French</hi> could run them down now at the same rate: They are awakned out of that Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargy they were in (<hi>Galli cantu</hi>) by the crowing of the Cock. And being convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced that they are not invincible, they will be more watchful, take stronger Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutions, and surer Measures, for the conservation of their Fortunes and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. And after all, in case they see themselves in an unavoidable necessity of being subdued by the <hi>French,</hi> in all likelihood they would do as they did in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s time, offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:199106:76"/> to the King of <hi>England,</hi> and become his Subjects, by a free giving up of themselves, and their Prerogatives. Which would prove an infinite advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage for <hi>England,</hi> and render it so ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible to the <hi>French,</hi> that lest this should happen, they will perhaps never at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the Conquest of <hi>Holland.</hi> For the Neighbourhood of the <hi>English</hi> would prove more prejudicial to them, than ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Spain Germany</hi> or <hi>Italy:</hi> For besides that no part of the World produces more resolute Men, and fitter for great Enterprizes; <hi>England</hi> is also most pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful by Sea, and abounds in Money. Whence such as are of this Opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that Great <hi>Britain</hi> may well gain, but cannot lose, in case the <hi>French</hi> sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due the <hi>Spanish</hi> Low Countries.</p>
            <p>The second Question was, whether the Conquest of <hi>Holland</hi> by the <hi>French,</hi> would prove of a dangerous conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence for <hi>England;</hi> whereupon I find the sentiments of most men divided, yet the generality say commonly <hi>Proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ardet Vcaligon,</hi> that Great <hi>Britain</hi> will be in danger of being overcome if the <hi>French</hi> are once Masters of <hi>Holland,</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:199106:76"/> the Reasons are: First, that in this case they would be Masters of the Seas and Trading, by joyning their Sea-Forces to the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> as likewise by taking possession of those great and rich Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies they have both in the East and West <hi>Indies.</hi> Which in few years would so impoverish <hi>England,</hi> that it would not be able to raise and entertain Armies great enough for its own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: And besides, would be of an easie access for the <hi>French,</hi> being now in pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session of the <hi>Holland</hi> - Harbours. Whence their Fleets would overun all our Seas, yea and put an affront upon us in our Harbours. The <hi>French</hi> in such a juncture of Affairs, would make the Conquest of <hi>England</hi> their only bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness; they would not say they court us for their own ends, as they do now, but make Peace with all the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, and apply themselves onely to <hi>England,</hi> as the last step to that long lookt-for Universal Monarchy; they could not want incouragement for such an Enterprize, being then strong enough to fight us by Sea; and their being wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted, would prove but a small Victory
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:199106:77"/> to us, and an inconsiderable loss to them. Now if we chance to be beat back to our Harbours, then the Conquest of some Sea-Town would be but an easie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; which the Enemy would instantly fortifie, so that it would scarce be in our power to take it again by storm, or a free Surrender, as being continually supplied with Men and Money, and all other Provisions, from the Ports of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Holland.</hi> But whereon such as discourse thus lay greatest stress, is the <hi>French</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that it would shew it self with more boldness than ever, fomented by the <hi>French</hi> Gold. This cursed Metal li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally distributed into many hands, would be a Seed of Sedition, &amp; of a secret fermentation, which would end at last in the ruine of the Nation; this <hi>Puissant</hi> Neighbour being perhaps to have in this case more secret Friends amongst us than open Enemies.</p>
            <p>But all this discourse, how well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded soever, is little regarded by others, who putting things in the worst suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, that is, of the <hi>French's</hi> being pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed of <hi>Holland,</hi> yet maintain the conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence thereof not to be so considerable,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:199106:77"/> as some people do vainly, as they fancy, apprehend it. For they consider the Empire of his Majesty of Great <hi>Britain,</hi> as another World separated from all its Neighbours by a deep Ditch (I mean the Sea) whereof the King of <hi>England</hi> is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute Master: So in such a case, because we would be in danger indeed, to see our Trading lost or lessened by the great number of Ships the <hi>French</hi> and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> together could set forth and man, <hi>England</hi> would set out such strong Navies, as would be able to secure it from both these inconveniencies. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides all this, they say, that in this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>impossible Supposition, the richest <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> and greatest Merchants would either retreat into the East <hi>Indies,</hi> where they are almost as powerful as in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> or distribute themselves into the chief Trading Cities of Christendom, as <hi>London</hi> especially, <hi>Hambourg,</hi> and other parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> because they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded they should not meet under the <hi>French</hi> Government, with the same in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements of Trading they have now. So this Conquest may prove a great disappointment for the <hi>French,</hi> and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:199106:78"/> a considerable advantage to the adjacent Countries, especially <hi>England;</hi> whither, no doubt, most of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> would retire, as being the happiest and easiest Government of <hi>Europe.</hi> As for a <hi>French</hi> Invasion, those that speak in this case, think it not much to be valued or fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For the Liberty of the Nation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then at the stake, all undoubtedly would agree against the common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, which would render all their At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts succesless. They confess the <hi>French</hi> Gold might dazle many, and do us more mischief than their Sword: But they answer, the Eye of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would be watchful over such as might be suspected to be bribed by the Enemy, and favour secretly and traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously his Designes. And that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the greatest part would; joyning hands against the <hi>French,</hi> force the rest to their Duty, or at least incapacitate the Traiterous and Seditious to be promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Enemies Interest.</p>
            <p>But now let us examine in the last instance, the third Question I proposed above, (<hi>viz.</hi>) Whether it be the real ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of <hi>France</hi> to attempt and make
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:199106:78"/> the Conquest of <hi>Holland.</hi> The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of men would wonder at such a Proposition, and stand to the affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, which, they will say, is so clear, that no man of common sence can denie it: For would not the addition of the United Provinces make the <hi>French</hi> King more Potent, both by Sea and Land? For if <hi>Holland</hi> were not both a rich and considerable corner of the World, why was the King of <hi>Spain</hi> so loth to part with it? what made the <hi>French</hi> King in Seventie two to Invade it, and the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> to oppose the whole Forces of the Empire, lest it should become a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>France?</hi> Can we then doubt in the least but that the Conquest of <hi>Holland</hi> would prove of an infinite ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the <hi>French,</hi> and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they would become richer, because of their being then Masters of the Trade, and more terrible to all their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, especially to <hi>England</hi> both by Sea and Land?</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding all those plausible reasons, several are of a contrary opinion, and perhaps the <hi>French</hi> also that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand best their own Interest, <hi>viz.</hi> That
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:199106:79"/> the Conquest of <hi>Holland</hi> would rather prove a disadvantage to the <hi>French,</hi> than a true advantage. For first, the main reason whereupon most men do ground their Opinion of the great advantages might redound to the <hi>French</hi> by such a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest, is, because they would thereby be Masters of the Trade: but this was else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where sufficiently answered; for besides that the <hi>English</hi> in this conjuncture would oppose by Sea such Forces as could maintain to themselves what they are now in possession of, I mean the freedom of Trading; <hi>Holland,</hi> as I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinuated above, if once conquered by the <hi>French,</hi> would instantly be deserted by all such as were possest of great Treasures, as being perswaded they could not long enjoy, under that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, what they had gain'd by their long Trading and Industry: The <hi>French</hi> then would have nothing or lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle left to make their market of, the Cities being now abandoned by the chief Citizens. I say nothing here of the great expences the <hi>French</hi> must of necessitie be at both by Sea and Land, when they go about making a Conquest
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:199106:79"/> of <hi>Holland.</hi> I desire onely the impartial Reader to make this reflection: That in case the <hi>French,</hi> which is not as yet near to be done, had subdued <hi>Holland,</hi> what infinite sums of money would be the cost of maintaining the <hi>Holland</hi> Dykes, without which, the whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try would be soon changed into a Sea? But you'll say, it would cost the <hi>French</hi> no more than it do's now the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> Whoever speaks thus, understands not the real difference between the <hi>French</hi> and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> in this case: The first have little or no Trading at all in the East <hi>Indies,</hi> so what monies they have need of for necessary expences, must come from <hi>France,</hi> and not from forreign Countries; which cannot prove but a notable diminution to the <hi>French</hi> Treasures. But supposing them how you will instated in the possession of <hi>Holland,</hi> what vast sums must be laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out in defending their Conquests, not from a forreign Enemy alone, but from the Invasion of a raging Sea? Now as to the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> their case is not the same, they spend indeed vast summs of money, in defending themselves from
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:199106:80"/> that furious Element. But you must consider that their East <hi>Indian</hi> Trade, as well as all <hi>Europe</hi> over, brings them in infinite Treasures: whereas the <hi>French</hi> would want all such supplies, as having no considerable establishment in the East <hi>Indies,</hi> or any other part of the World (as to Trading.) For it may be supposed, that no man will be so foolish as to think that the Conquest of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> would import the Conquest of whatever the <hi>Hollanders</hi> are possessed of elsewhere; without which, it would prove more burdensome to the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour than profitable. There is as yet another thing that would prove ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely disadvantageous to the <hi>French;</hi> if they subdued <hi>Holland,</hi> they would be lookt upon then by all the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> as aspiring to an Universal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy; so the <hi>Germans, Spaniards,</hi> and <hi>English</hi> in this case would joyn their Forces, to the utter destruction of the <hi>French,</hi> who could not in all likelihood resist so many, and so powerful Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, <hi>England</hi> alone being an equal Match for <hi>France,</hi> if not divided by Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Wars and Intestine Broils. The
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:199106:80"/>
               <hi>French,</hi> 'tis true, resisted in these late Wars, and with advantage the <hi>Germans, Spaniards,</hi> and <hi>Hollanders;</hi> but undou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>btedly had not the <hi>English, Scots,</hi> and <hi>Irish</hi> been on their side against the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> they had easily been overcome by the Forces of the Empire. How near was <hi>Turenne</hi> being beat in the first Battle of the late Wars at <hi>Sensim</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the late Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prara,</hi> had not the Earl of <hi>Dumborton</hi> beaten back with his Infantry the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Horse, and retaken the Cannon lost by the <hi>French?</hi> What service did not our Troops in the Battle of <hi>Strasburg,</hi> where they took several pieces of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non from the Enemy, and at <hi>Colmar</hi> against the Marquess of <hi>Brandenburg.</hi> in the passage of the <hi>Rhine</hi> after the Death of <hi>Turenne,</hi> and at the Siege of <hi>Freiburg</hi> in <hi>Brisgo</hi> in a most rigorous season? In all which occasions, the <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>English</hi> render'd such notable service to the <hi>French,</hi> that 'tis credibly believ'd <hi>France</hi> without their assistance had been laid open on that side to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:199106:81"/>
            <p>Out of all this we may conclude, or at least frame a doubt of no small weight, Whether ever he will really undertake the Conquest of <hi>Holland:</hi> Whereof, as was surmized, they had no real design <hi>Anno</hi> 1672. but onely to humble the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> for that, as they alleadged, they took too much upon 'em, to the prejudice of the <hi>French</hi> Interest; yet seeing they yielded up so easily their strongest holds and Cities, without any considerable resistance, they could not but pursue their good fortune, so long as it smil'd upon'em, and they met no rubs. But they no sooner perceived the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, Spaniards,</hi> and <hi>Hollanders</hi> in an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fensive and Defensive League against them, but they made use of all their Politicks, and utmost Endeavours, to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a part of their Conquests by a sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Peace, in the midst of their Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; which they at length concluded with the <hi>Hollanders</hi> apart, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with the rest of their Enemies, to their best advantage, either joyntly or severally. So we may observe, what I have heard confessed by some of the eminent States-men of <hi>France,</hi> that
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:199106:81"/> the <hi>French</hi> manage no Nation so much as the <hi>English,</hi> as fearing none so much, and having never been overcome by any other. The main Interest then of the <hi>French,</hi> if it be lawful for us to dive into such secrets, is to possess them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves of the Low Countries, and leave the <hi>Hollanders</hi> in a full possession of all their Trading and Priviledges. For by this means they would ingage them in their interest, and perhaps to buy their Freedom and Liberties with a yearly Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute: and upon this account onely, or at least chiefly, the Conquest of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish</hi> Low Countries might prove pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to <hi>England;</hi> for in this Juncture of Affairs, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> would perhaps comply rather with the <hi>French</hi> than with the <hi>English,</hi> unless, as I said else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, (which I am of opinion they would do) they judged it more their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest to make a free Gift of themselves to the King of Great <hi>Britain;</hi> who in that case would protect them both by Sea and by Land as his own Subjects.</p>
            <div type="remarks">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:199106:82"/>
               <p>I shall now put a period to this Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, with some Remarks on the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of fact; wherein, as I take, I give the liberty of Prophecying. And</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether the Retreat, or rather Flight of the Imperial Army at the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and before their laying Siege to <hi>Vienna,</hi> was to the advantage or disadvantage of that place.</p>
               <p>'Tis odd to commence with a Dilem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, and at the same time confess a loss and a gain; But were there not mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures in both, I should conclude 'twas an ill Omen to begin a Campain with bad success, not onely in respect to the Influence it has on the early Opinions of the People, which they are too apt to retain, but for the real loss. The real loss in this case was not of more than a thousand, but the frighted amounted to many thousands. When again I consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the gain by this loss, I can scarce al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the bad turn to be so. What coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance this retreating Army gave to <hi>Vienna,</hi> and what means it furnished them with, for the providing and fitting
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:199106:82"/> all necessaries and Warlike Apparatus, for the better carrying on, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining their defence; may best be judged by what was after their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thither, beginning first with the Escape, or safe Retreat of his Imperial Majesty; the Recieving considerable quantities of Powder and Shot into the place; the fitting of new and old Platforms, and raising Palizadoes; time for the destroying the Houses and Gardens nearest the Town; lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of burning the Suburbs; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other things necessary, after the appearance of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vesting <hi>Vienna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, had this Army been destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or so much weakened, that the <hi>Turks</hi> had no further cause to fear them, whilst they ravaged the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, or intercepted the Passages, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the other Imperial Cities and <hi>Vienna;</hi> I know not whither it might have tended. Perhaps it might have been the hard fate of the Emperour, the Remnant of a Routed Army, and many others, to have fallen into the hands of their Enemies. At best but
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:199106:83"/> the remaining in that place, there to have undergon the brunt of the War, and the want, not only of necessary Provisions, which must have been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry extraordinary for such a number of people necessary, and unnecessary. And also in all probability, lost the means of relieving, or securing that place (whatever would have been its insluence on <hi>Germany</hi>) through the occasion of the Restraint of his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Majesty, and his chief Ministers there, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Whether the</hi> Turks <hi>were successful in their Mining?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> indeed were very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with their Mines, having sprung Two by the Twenty third of <hi>July;</hi> yet before they could throw down the Two Faces of the <hi>Lebel Bastion,</hi> 'twas the Sixth of <hi>September:</hi> After having made use of more than Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty two Mines, besides those that were discovered, vented, and frustrated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore considering the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude they had to improve the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages gained by their Mines, the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess did not result to expectation.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:199106:83"/>3. <hi>Whether the Garison was successful in Mining?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Mines the Garison sprung were about half a Score, and those they frustrated of the Enemies, about half that number, the success whereof was not overmuch: Which, whither it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y be imputed to their want of Skill, or Courage, to prosecute, or prevent; or the general uncertainty of these Subterranean Works, I leave the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to others, with this too, That there were about Fifty Mines in the whole. The General opinion was, that the Defenders were herein defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>What was the Execution done by the Great Guns of the Enemy?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though in the last Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> not having Great Guns, was reputed a principal cause of <hi>Solyman</hi>'s ill success (which piece of Service 'tis said the Emperour purchased of the then Grand Vizier, a favourer of the Christians he had deserted) it could not now be assigned; such is either the difference of times, or change of method: For now they had not only
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:199106:84"/> store of Great, but very extraordinary Ordnance; of whose use at present, they have more reason to be perfect in, than heretofore: Yet herein was not the Service extraordinary; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the disabling some few Guns, and the Plying too warmly, on an imperfect Bastion, they made no Breaches considerable: So that had not their Mines been more effectual than their Batteries, they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have taken the place. An exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whereof I would instance in the little effect their Great Guns had on the Ravelin (or Half-Moon) on which independent piece of Fortification, they made their Efforts until <hi>September</hi> the Third: At which time too, it was not taken; but burned and deserted by the Besieged: Though it must be confessed they annoyed the Garison sometimes with their Stones.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>What was the Execution done by the Bombs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Murdering Engine that does its part every where, had but a small share here on either side; for besides the burning the Great Hall of <hi>Buchaim,</hi>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:199106:84"/> it did little mifchief else. And though the <hi>Turks</hi> Bombs have sometimes fallen among the Garisons Mortar-pieces and Ordnance, and gave Fire to them, they have participated of the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as well as the Besieged.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>What was the defect of the</hi> Lebel-<hi>Bastion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The greatest stress of the Siege lay upon the <hi>Court</hi> and <hi>Lebel</hi> Bastions, the latter of which was very defective, and which is an oversight in all Basti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>viz.</hi> the wanting of Room, and being too scanty of convenience for the placing and playing of the Cannon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to advantage. It is usual to judge of the strength of a place, by the number of times it hath been Besieged; and therefore since this weakness is so well known, it may be hoped that that, as well as other such, will be prevented for the future.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>What were the Accidents of Fire?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though the Burning of the <hi>Suburbs,</hi> and the <hi>Scotch-Court,</hi> at the same time, <hi>July</hi> the Fourteenth, might be looked on, as the communication of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers Flame to the latter: yet few
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:199106:85"/> were of that opinion, it being gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally thought, that that Fire which reduced the <hi>Scotch Court,</hi> and several other Houses to Ashes, was a thing designed for the Blowing up of the Magazine of Stores and Powder, which very narrowly escaped. But had it happened, how soon would <hi>Vienna</hi> have been lost? and how much before the time, had the death of a great many been anticipated?</p>
               <p n="8">8 <hi>What were the casualties of Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Bloody-Flux,</hi> though it raged more without, yet the slaughter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in was more felt; and notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it may be reckoned among the usual and common calamities attending such enterprizes, it had a more than uncommon Influence on this Garison. For-had it so happened, that it had been an earlier Distemper among them, the Relief that rescued them from this Mortality, and that of the Sword, would have come too late.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>What influence a Commander hath on his Soldiers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How much the Issue of an Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:199106:85"/> depends upon the wellfare of a Chief, is not this days question; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it be judged how feelingly the Besieged were concerned for Count <hi>Staremberg,</hi> whilst as then the Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of his Wounds was not doubted, for want of his appearaoce: So uneasy are a people that think themselves not safe, but under the Eye of their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Of the Advantages and Disad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of either in General.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though under such circumstances of disproportion, we ought always to give the Advantage to the Number; yet considering the performances of the Defendants, they have by much surpassed the Assailants. The Besieged have, in some of their Sallies, been very successful; but generally other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise: Their necessities for the most part forcing them upon this. And what is their Disadvantage, that after they are got out as far as they can, they must return to the same place they came out at; and may be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted: Yet of this sort we may reckon about a score. The Skirmishes,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:199106:86"/> Attacks, Assaults, and other Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, are scarce to be numbred, and each have had their share of success; but whenever the Adventure hath been indifferent, the goodness of the one, hath equalled the number of the other: And there is some ground to believe, that whenever the Garison should have been lost, it must have preceeded from the effects of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Mines, and not from their Force.</p>
               <p>The taking of the Enemies Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons of necessaries; the Disappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Teckely</hi> at <hi>Presbourg;</hi> the Want of Bullets in the Camp, which made them discontinue their Batteries for some whole days, and at times something sparingly, making use of Pummels of Swords, all sorts of Iron and Stones; the Imperial Armies streightning their Convoys, by hover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about; the cutting off a Party of <hi>Tartars</hi> in the Woods of <hi>Vienna,</hi> the taking of a Pass in the Wood of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna</hi> sometime before the Relief; and many other things of the like nature, may be reckoned among the Disad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages or Misfortunes of the <hi>Turks</hi>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:199106:86"/> in this Enterprize, and conducive to their Miscarriage; and may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted among the Providences of the Almighty, for the good of <hi>Vienna</hi> and the <hi>German</hi> Empire: Yet whenever they suffer themselves in such a state to be surprized for the future, they are accountable to their own follies for neglecting the Means; for they are not always to expect God should work by Miracles.</p>
               <p>And thus I have finished this Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Vienna:</hi> But cannot leave the Affair in hand, all things therein being so remarkable: <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:199106:87"/>
               <head>A further Account of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress of the Imperial Army, after the Relief of <hi>Vienna.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving need of a quick Pen, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Victorious Steps of the Imperial Army, after their happy suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess of Relieving <hi>Vienna;</hi> and beating the whole <hi>Ottoman</hi> forces: By the <hi>7th.</hi> of <hi>October</hi> we shall find the resolute King of <hi>Poland,</hi> with only his own Forces, engaging the <hi>Turks</hi> near <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kan:</hi> But this being the last stake of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Game in these Parts, we are not to wonder, if he find herein, hotter work than he expected; and where at once is to be played off, the Fortune of the Kingdom of <hi>Hungary.</hi> The Grand Vizier, to give a stop to the Advance of the Imperial Troops, Mustered up, out of all the Fragments of his scattered Army, the choicest of his Troops and <hi>Veteran</hi> Soldiers; and form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them into a Body, under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of several of the <hi>Bassa's</hi> of the best account, resolved by another Essay,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:199106:87"/> either to retrieve his lost Honour, or stem the Current of his adverse Fortune. The Engagement proved very severe to the King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s Forces, who having not been used to Retreat, found it very hard to stand the shock of this unequal Force; and what had been the Issue, had not the arrival of some of the Imperial <hi>Dragoons</hi> (that immediately upon notice of his Adventure, were dispatch'd for his Reinforcement) changed the face of affairs, 'tis hard to Judge. The <hi>Turks</hi> having given so fair a push for a Victory, tho' they could not attain thereto, might well think, after the arrival of fresh Forces, their Attempts would be more ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous; and that as the first, or least loss is always best, the retiring in time, before their Body was dissordered, or weakned, 'twould seem to make it at their Election, to quit the Ground they could not maintain: By this means, the King of <hi>Poland</hi> acquitted himself with great Honour, though not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great danger: and Prince <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> the Son of such a Father, would
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:199106:88"/> not have been behind him, had not the killing of his Horse under him, stopt his Career. On the <hi>18th.</hi> of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> the rest of the Imperial Army came up, and joyned with the King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s Forces. On the <hi>9th.</hi> the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and Count <hi>Staremberg</hi> came to a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel with the <hi>Turks,</hi> who were in a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Thirteen or Fourteen thousand strong, and seemed not unwilling to embrace the Oppertunity. For the <hi>Turks</hi> encouraged with the late advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage on the <hi>Poles,</hi> the <hi>7th.</hi> past, no sooner saw the Christian Army Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance in order of Battle, the <hi>Imperia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists</hi> having this Van-Guard; but with Fury and Noise, they first attacked the <hi>Imperialists,</hi> and afterwards the <hi>Poles;</hi> by both which they were so warmly received, and followed, that after a dispute of some hours, the Honour of the day fell to the Christians; and of this whole Body of <hi>Turks,</hi> not above Four thousand escaped: the rest being either killed or drowned, by the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Bridge of Boats that led to <hi>Gran;</hi> or taken Prisoners. So that <hi>Barkan,</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:199106:88"/> after the defeat of this Army, that was appointed for their Defence, and of the Bridge, made little resistance; for immediately upon the taking of the Counterscarp by Storm, and putting the Defendants to the Sword, the Garison yeilded on Discretion; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there was Five hundred <hi>Janizaries,</hi> to whom they gave Quarter. The Plunder of this place, and the <hi>Turkish</hi> Camp, was very great; the stores of Ammunition and Provisions very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable; about Twenty pieces of Cannon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> taken: And in fine, the loss of the <hi>Turks,</hi> by this defeat, is so great a Blow to them, that it is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally believed, they will not be able for the future, to make any reasonable Opposition to the Christian Forces. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> after having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired <hi>Barkan,</hi> and put a good Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison into it, advanced towards <hi>Gran,</hi> by a Bridge of Boats (brought from <hi>Comorra</hi>) over the <hi>Danube,</hi> about half a mile above <hi>Gran,</hi> taking the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a small Island in the River, wherein he raised a small Fort, for the security of the Bridge.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:199106:89"/>
               <p>This City of <hi>Gran</hi> (or <hi>Strigonium</hi>) lies on the South-side of the <hi>Danube,</hi> not far from the place of the uniting of the River <hi>Gran</hi> with the <hi>Danube.</hi> Its divided into the Upper and Lower, and both Walled, the lower Wall commands the <hi>Danube,</hi> and St. <hi>Thomas</hi>'s Hill commands the Town, which is likewise Walled. In this place was the first Christian King St. <hi>Stephen</hi> born; and King <hi>Stephen</hi> the third here Buried. It hath been famous for the many Sieges it hath sustained; but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous for the last base and ignoble delivery of it into the hands of the <hi>Turks.</hi> It hath been the Metropolitan City of <hi>Hungary;</hi> but at present not of that regard, the principal fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being much damnified and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and their best Cannon, and the greatest part of their Ammunition sent away to the Siege of <hi>Vienna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Imperialists</hi> having passed the <hi>Danube</hi> on the Twentieth of <hi>October,</hi> laid Siege to <hi>Gran;</hi> they began with the Fort on St. <hi>Thomas</hi>'s Hill, having therein a Garison of about Four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Janizaries,</hi> which they took, sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:199106:89"/> the greatest part of the Buildings the <hi>Turks</hi> had set on Fire. On this Hill the Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi> raised a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery against the Town, which soon made the <hi>Turks</hi> abondon the Town, and retire into the Cittadel; but that also being quickly too hot for them, on the 27th the <hi>Turks</hi> desired to Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulate, which being assented unto, and the Articles agreed, the Soldiers March<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out to the Number of Two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand <hi>Janizaries,</hi> and the Inhabitants Four thousand, making their way to <hi>Buday</hi> under an Imperial Convoy. Thus, after Seventy eight years being in the hands of the <hi>Turks,</hi> this impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant place came into the possession of the Christians; together with Eighteen Pieces of Cannon, Four hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand pound of Powder, and considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble stores of Provisions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having added <hi>Gran</hi> to the other Conquests, let us have an Eye on what is done elsewhere; in one place we shall find the Christian Forces Marching towards <hi>New-hausel,</hi> either to take it, or Block it up: And though its said to be a Garison of Twelve
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:199106:90"/> thousand <hi>Janizaries,</hi> they have already made Addresses to the Duke of <hi>Lorain,</hi> and offered to deliver it up on Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. This great Garison being Block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up by the taking of <hi>Gran,</hi> for want of Provisions, will not be able to hold out the Winter, and therefore must not think to stand upon Terms.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Croats,</hi> Troops of <hi>Stiria,</hi> and the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> are intent on the Blocking up <hi>Canisia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Poland,</hi> reinforced with the Troops of <hi>Lithuania,</hi> is Marching towards <hi>Agria,</hi> to possess himself of that, and some other places in the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>Hungary,</hi> for the security of his Winter Quarters.</p>
               <p>The Grand Viziers Army Disbands it self, and he is retired from <hi>Stoel-Wei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stenburg</hi> (or <hi>Alba Regalis</hi>) towards <hi>Belgrade,</hi> leaving <hi>Buda</hi> under the Charge of two Bassa's.</p>
               <p>And if, as it is believed, <hi>Buda</hi> and <hi>Pest</hi> will be Attacked, before the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians take up their Winter Quarters; In this Consternation of the <hi>Turks;</hi> I see not what should hinder the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of all <hi>Hungary.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="222" facs="tcp:199106:90"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>